<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The constant man's character. Intended to be sent first as a letter from a gentleman in the country, to a gentlemen his esteemed friend and countryman, a Member of the House of Commons. Since inlarged into a discourse by way of humble advice to keep him from revolting, either directly or collaterally by the side-winde of being Presbyterially affected, through the mistaken and unhappy conceit, that those who have taken the Covenant, cannot without breach of the same, assent and submit unto the late proceedings of the Parliament, when as the parts of the Covenant seem to be inconsistent within themselves, as the author's observations here discoursed do manifest. The scope whereof is 1 Historically to set down the occasion and beginnings of the war. ... 4 To prove the fitness and necessity (as matters now stand) of complying with, and submitting unto this present government. For the powers that be are ordained of God, Rom. 13. Together with some animadversions incident hereunto on the same book, and on the two declarations, intituled The declarations of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament at Oxford. The one touching a treaty for peace, [the] other concerning their endeavors for peace. Printed there, 1643.</title>
            <author>S. W.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 158 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96074</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E595_7</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204161</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863846</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863846</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116061</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96074)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116061)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 91:E595[7])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The constant man's character. Intended to be sent first as a letter from a gentleman in the country, to a gentlemen his esteemed friend and countryman, a Member of the House of Commons. Since inlarged into a discourse by way of humble advice to keep him from revolting, either directly or collaterally by the side-winde of being Presbyterially affected, through the mistaken and unhappy conceit, that those who have taken the Covenant, cannot without breach of the same, assent and submit unto the late proceedings of the Parliament, when as the parts of the Covenant seem to be inconsistent within themselves, as the author's observations here discoursed do manifest. The scope whereof is 1 Historically to set down the occasion and beginnings of the war. ... 4 To prove the fitness and necessity (as matters now stand) of complying with, and submitting unto this present government. For the powers that be are ordained of God, Rom. 13. Together with some animadversions incident hereunto on the same book, and on the two declarations, intituled The declarations of the Lords and Commons assembled in Parliament at Oxford. The one touching a treaty for peace, [the] other concerning their endeavors for peace. Printed there, 1643.</title>
                  <author>S. W.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 77, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Giles Calvert at the Black Spread-Eagle, neer the west end of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed at end: S.W.</note>
                  <note>The numbers 1-4 are enclosed in brackets on title page. The words "One touching .. endeavors for peace." are enclosed in brackets with the word "The" printed once to the left of the brackets.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Mar. 18"; the imprint date has been altered to 1649.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Church history --  17th century --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116061:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Conſtant Man's Character.</hi> Intended to be ſent firſt as a LETTER FROM A Gentleman in the Country, to a Gentleman his eſteemed Friend and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryman, a Member of the Houſe of <hi>Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since inlarged into a DISCOURSE by way of humble ADVICE to keep him from Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volting, either directly or collaterally by the ſide-winde of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Presbyterially</hi> affected, through the miſtaken and unhappy conceit, <hi>That thoſe who have taken the Covenant, cannot without breach of the ſame, aſſent and ſubmit unto the late proceedings of the Parliament,</hi> when as the parts of the <hi>Covenant</hi> ſeem to be inconſiſtent within themſelves, as the Author's Obſervations here diſcourſed do manifeſt.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="4">The Scope whereof is</cell>
                     <cell>1</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Hiſtorically to ſet down the Occaſion and Beginnings of the War.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>2</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To ſhew That the Parliament had no intention to leavy a War.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>3</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>That the Book called</hi> 
                        <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>is probably none of the King's.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>4</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>To prove the fitneſs and neceſſity (as matters now ſtand) of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with, and ſubmitting unto this preſent Government. For the Powers</hi> that be <hi>are Ordained of God,</hi> Rom. 13.</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Together With ſome Animadverſions incident hereunto on the ſame Book, and on the two Declarations, intituled <hi>The Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of the Lords and Commons aſſembled in Parliament at</hi> OXFORD.</p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2">The</cell>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>One touching a Treaty for Peace,</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell rows="2">Printed there, 1643.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <hi>Other concerning their Endeavors for Peace.</hi>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Giles Calvert</hi> at the <hi>Black Spread-Eagle,</hi> neer the Weſt End of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:116061:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:116061:2"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Letter, rather this Narra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is founded on a Diſcourſe had betwixt two Gentlemen; the one unto whom it was written, having the abler parts of Wit and Speech: the other, the Writer, having the juſter cauſe, or at leaſt he judged it ſo; the weakneſs of whoſe judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment may indeed be an Objection againſt the credit of the Work, there being three means onely whereby to diſcern and report a Truth, Judgment, Knowledg, Conſcience; the two firſt (Judgment, Knowledg in State-affairs) the Author may be defective in the ſtrength thereof; notwithſtanding, in that he is neither engaged againſt the one, nor obliged to the other Party, other wiſe then by a common du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, his judgment may ſeem the more right and clear by reaſon his Obligations are the leſs,
<pb facs="tcp:116061:3"/>
wherefore that which may be ſaid in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half is, That <hi>the Conſcience and upright Truth, by which he hath meaſured what he hath written, is free from Faction or Partiality.</hi> The danger where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto a Writer in Divided and Seditious Times expoſeth himſelf, is known unto all men; when whatſoever is received with Applauſe or Liking by the one, is therefore rejected with Deſpight and Scorn by the other ſide. The Promiſe and <note n="*" place="margin">See the Proteſtation taken, <hi>May,</hi> 1641. where the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors Vow <hi>by all good wayes and means to bring to condigne Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment all ſuch as ſhal by Force, Practice, Councels, Plots and Conſpiracies, or otherwiſe do any thing to the contrary in this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation;</hi> and further that he ſhall <hi>in all iuſt ways endeavour to preſerve the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion and Peace betwixt the three Kingdoms,</hi> &amp;c.</note> Proteſtation made to <hi>Endeavour by all juſt ways,</hi> out-weighs the Danger. In this Diſcourſe he arrogates nothing to himſelf, but an even and true delivery of what he hath obſerved and is well known, much leſs doth he think his ſtrength or skill, enough to help either ſide to Victory: but according to his weak and ſpent abilities to endeavour the reſtoring the three Nations to their former Peace, their mutual Intereſts and Rights, unto which the only and next way is, to deliver and uprightly to ſet down the truth. A more able Pen-man may ſhew it more excellently, <hi>None can ſhew a more excellent way.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116061:3"/>
            <head>The Conſtant Man's Character.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Know not how this Diſcourſe may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh, aſſure your ſelf, ſent from the hand and heart of him who loves and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours you; howbeit wiſe men leaning on their own wiſdoms, and ſacrificing too much peradventure to their own Net, commonly neither need nor care for the affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of their weaker friends. What I am in relation un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, or in the rank of them, is known to thoſe who know us both; what in my ſelf, I am conſcious of wanting Experience and Learning to derive any knowledg from antiquated Times or Hiſtories, for the faſhioning this into an elegant and polite work, but in a downright way to fall on, familiarly and plainly to ſet down the beginnings and firſt entrance into this preſent War; which when it firſt broke out, that the Gentlemen of this County did declare themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to what Party they would adhere, Two eminent Leaders on the Parliaments ſide, Sir <hi>R. C.</hi> and your ſelf, out-weighing, as we judged, ſo many more of the oppoſite Party, did ſeem to joyn and go one way for the Priviledges of that Court, and the Subject's Liberties; The infringing which, added to ſome late Jealouſies, was the firſt Aſcent to theſe Diviſions; how,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116061:4"/>
and by what degrees it went higher, follows in this Diſcourſe. In your reſenting which, He as a Member of the Houſe, You as a Patriot of the Country, We could not think Ye did it in a light, Factious or Sediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous way, but as having ſeriouſly weighed, and by your Readings even before and ſince the beginning of this War known, That <hi>the Inſtitution of Parliaments was had and made by an Ancient, Neceſſary, and wholſome Law,</hi> That the Power, Priviledges, and Authority thereof were to be kept inviolable and entire, That as to this preſent Parliament, the King Himſelf in <note n="a" place="margin">See His Anſwer to a Declaration from both Houſes in <hi>May</hi> 1642.</note> His Anſwer to a Declaration ſent Him from both Houſes of Lords and Commons, doth confeſs and allow <hi>Them a full and juridicall power to judg and determine the moſt doubtfull, high and weightieſt Crimes and Cauſes,</hi> although He ſeems to limit it <hi>by particular Caſes, &amp; regularly brought before them;</hi> acknowledging withall (together with the <note n="b" place="margin">See the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Lords &amp; Commons aſſembled in Parliament (as they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it) at Oxford, 1643. <hi>Pa.</hi> 12.</note> Lords and Commons aſſembled at Oxford) <hi>The Priviledg of Parliament to be ſo ſubſtantiall and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire a Right, that the Invaſion of the Liberties of either Houſe, is an Injury to the other, and to the whole Kingdom.</hi> In ſeverall His Meſſages returned unto their Propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, He repeats and confirms the ſame judgment of their full and ample Power, being legally ſummoned, and <hi>By a Law conſented unto by Him in full Parliament, not to be diſſolved, unleſs by their own conſent.</hi> Notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding which, ſeveral attempts of force and violence were offered, as far as His Party's Power could extend it ſelf, to the diſſolving it, by contending to divide and ſcatter Them, accuſing the remaining part of the Members ſitting in the Houſe <hi>of being Rebels,</hi> ſo being divided, to account no other of the Parliament at Weſtminſter, then He doth of the Parliament in Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116061:4"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">In His Declaration concerning His Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings with His Subjects of Scotland, ſince the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cification in the Camp neer Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick, printed 1640. <hi>pa.</hi> 38.</note> 
               <hi>The divided Members of that diſtracted Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Body remaining at Edenburgh.</hi> So that as to the Parliament of England, it muſt be confeſſed, that He meant not what He expreſſed in allowing that Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of Power, or that His Party hath ſince prevailed with Him to renounce that judgment which He de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared to have had of Them, That the contentions at the firſt ſitting of the Houſe were, upon the point, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout matters of Fact, what things were done, what at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to be done, how the King and His Miniſters of Juſtice had demeaned themſelves ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of His Raign, how many Oppreſſions of ſeverall kindes had been offered by them, how they had of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended againſt the Known and Fundamentall Laws in an Arbitrary way of Government; The Queſtion then tacitely diſputed in all mens hearts, betwixt Thoſe <hi>who would that He ſhould go on to do what He pleaſed,</hi> and Thoſe <hi>who contended to have Him govern according to the Laws,</hi> Whether there were any Power in being to emulate and check a King's, except a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments? That this Parliament in contending to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the one againſt the other, was interrupted and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, and as the Scots aver, <note n="b" place="margin">See the Scots Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrance, 1640. cited by M. <hi>Tho. May,</hi> in his Hiſtory of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of England, written 1647.</note> 
               <hi>For no other reaſon cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, then to give the King relief and ayd againſt their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming into England;</hi> on which grounds they ſent to the Parliament of England a Juſtification of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, intreating Them to be <hi>wary in vindicating their own Laws and Liberties, to fruſtrate the Deſigns of thoſe Evill Counſellours, who had procured this Parliament for no other end, then to arm the King with warlike ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes againſt His Scottiſh Subjects, and by that War to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlave, if not to ruine both Nations. That after many vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and diſſolutions of Parliaments in England, This</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:116061:5"/>
               <hi>was not to redreſs Grievances, but to be ſo over-reached, if They were not carefull and couragious, that no poſsibility ſhould be left for the future redreſsing any; That ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Practices might be well ſuſpected, when at the ſame time a Parliament was denyed to</hi> Scotland, <hi>although pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed on the word of a King, granted to</hi> England <hi>when not expected, and obtruded upon</hi> Ireland <hi>when not deſired.</hi> The Riſe of all which was from the Anger which the Scots knew the King conceived againſt them for ſome particular acts of theirs, charged with diſloyalty: as That they refuſed and declared (amongſt other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters) againſt His Meſſages ſent them to receive the Service Book obtruded on them; for which, as for Vindicating themſelves from the like charged Diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties, they were Accuſed by the King to have wrote a <note n="a" place="margin">Cited and complained of by the King in the ſame Declaration againſt His Scottiſh Subjects, for inviting Forreign Powers into this Kingdom <hi>Pag.</hi> 56, 57. See the Letter it ſelf in the ſame Declaration, Signed by ſeven of the principall of the Nobility of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
               </note> Letter to the King of France, <hi>imploring His Protection, as wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their Obedience to their own King.</hi> For which diſloyall Letter (as it was termed) a chief <note n="b" place="margin">The Lord <hi>Louden.</hi> See in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent excuſe.</note> Peer of theirs was impriſoned, and condemned to die; That the Pacifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation had and made to take away all differences paſt, and which might enſue betwixt the King, the Engliſh and the Scots, by the prudent and joynt advice of a ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect Committee of Engliſh and Scottiſh Lords, as to remove all jealouſies betwixt both Nations, was ſoon after it was made, ſcorned and ſlighted: The Scots then complaining in their Informations made unto the <note place="margin">See the ſame Book.</note> Engliſh their Friends and Brethren, of many injuries they had received ſince the Pacification made, and contrary to that Agreement, This the Condition then
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116061:5"/>
of the Scots: Theſe the very words of their Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, <hi>That the Vnion and Brotherly League entered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to by both Nations, was in the King's Indignation no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe conſtrued then an Invitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the One, and Invaſion of</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">See the King's accompt of them, how in the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> He keeps it in me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory, <hi>That they were the firſt that began His troubles,</hi> in the Treatiſe of His leaving Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, and going to the Scots, and elſwhere in ſeverall places of that Book. Alſo in the Declaration printed on the King's behalf at Oxford, 1643. <hi>Page</hi> 23. Suggeſting an intent in them to confound the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and alter the Laws of England, <hi>p.</hi> 28. The Marqueſſe of <hi>Montroſſe</hi> declareth how they began His Troubles <hi>(viz.)</hi> by diſperſing their Apologeticall Pamphlets, as he terms them, through great Brittain, before the troubles began, and before their coming with an Army into England. See a Book entituled, The Hiſtory of His Majeſty's Affairs under the Conduct of the Marqueſſe in the yeers 1644, 1645, 1646. <hi>Page</hi> 3.</note> 
               <hi>Forreigners in the other Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; and howſoever the Charge in the ſeven Articles exhibited a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſix Members of both Houſes was laid to thoſe few only, yet probably it had reached many other of the Engliſh Nation, had not the firſt aſſault of Violence in the King's Party miſcarryed as it did.</hi> So many ſad and direfull notes could not but portend a War againſt one, or both Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, as Time and Opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſhould beſt ſerve to manage the Deſign in hand, or elſe the Parliament knowing themſelves to be a free and full Convention, in all parts a Parliament, both in the Subſtance and Form <hi>(Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moned by the King's Writ to meet, &amp;c.)</hi> as in the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Time</hi> and <hi>Place,</hi> muſt ſubmit to the Will and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of an <note n="b" place="margin">Amongſt other motives to His anger, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the E. of <hi>Strafford's</hi> death, which whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther He would have avenged on the Party who condemned him, may be gueſſed at, in that He, or an unknown Author in His name, ſeverall times repents the injuſtice of that act, <hi>How Himſelf was forced to yeeld complyance: for which ſin, as He mentions it, He and His Kingdoms have felt long, great, and heavy troubles.</hi> See the ſame Book, in the Treatiſe concerning the E. of <hi>Strafford:</hi> and the Marq. of <hi>Montroſſe</hi> his Declaration, ſet forth 1649. aggravating the ſame, to incenſe the King and His Party againſt the Scots, expreſſing in it their diſloyall practices, breach of Duty, Covenants, calling them Traytors, &amp;c.</note> incenſed King: So to be Diſſolved or Awed at pleaſure, or to have Boundaries put upon their Acts and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels by ſuch as they knew to be corrupt, and would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116061:6"/>
from the King, <hi>To the end His Throne might be eſtabliſhed:</hi> That in this agony and doubt, whether They ſhould Submit, Deſiſt, or Act according to their Truſt, they thought it neerly land neceſſarily concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned them to provide for the publique welfare, for their own and the Kingdoms ſafety, ſome of their Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers being impeached and charged, two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms provoked and menaced, the <note n="a" place="margin">See the King's gratefull acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the affection and loyalty of His I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh Subjects, in offering to ſupply Him with Preparations, &amp;c. together with their Perſons and Eſtates, even to the uttermoſt of their ability, to reduce His diſ-affected Subjects of Scotland to their obedience; deſiring withall, It may be recorded as an Ordinance of Parliament, and to be printed as a teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of their Loyalty to all the world, and to ſucceeding ages; which could not but ſtir up the Scots to ſeek protection and aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from their fellow-Subjects and Friends whereſoever; whom the King call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed His diſ-affected Subjects, and how He doth ſecern them from the reſt, is hard to judg; when as the whole and moſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable part of that Kingdom did by their Pacts and Counſels at their Aſſemblies held, withſtand and reſolve to withſtand di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of His Meſſages, obtruding on them ſuch matters as made againſt the Peace of their Church and Kingdom. See His De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration ſince the Pacification. <hi>Page</hi> 63.</note> third alſo likely to bear a part in the broyls of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two, the King Himſelf jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous and diſpleaſed to ſee the Parliament, then at diſtance with Him in tranſaction of matters concerning the three Kingdoms, Petitioned and Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed unto (termed in an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious and ſcornfull way by ſome of His Party, <hi>Omnipotent;</hi> Others murmuringly upbraid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that it was <hi>Idolized)</hi> Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as it were neglected and left out, none or ſeldom Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes made to Him. So the Parliament had a narrow path to tread between their hopes to regain the King's loſt Favour, after many evidences of His Anger poured forth, and their hazarding the ruine of thoſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples which by their Duty and Covenant they were to aſſert and defend: What thoſe Principles were, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows in this Diſcourſe; if rightly caſt up, but two in chief, <hi>The ſecuring the Proteſtant Religion,</hi> the <hi>Primu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, The preſerving the Laws and Peace,</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Suprema Lex, ſalus Populi.</note> the chiefeſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:116061:6"/>
Law, the Peoples Safety: The other Principles are ſubſervient onely, and fall in by complication and dependency upon thoſe two, as the means unto the end. Laſtly, Sir, That this Parliament thus acting, You ſtrenuouſly argued, as knowing well that their Cauſe was juſt, their War Defenſive, when ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <note n="a" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Denz. Hollis</hi> his Speech, <hi>June</hi> 1642.</note> Gentleman of the like abilities with you, had in an excellent Speech delivered to that purpoſe, <hi>That there was a ſucceſsion of Deſignes to interrupt it; as firſt by awing and taking away the Freedom of it by an Army:</hi> then, <hi>actually aſſaulting it, and with the Sword to cut aſunder the onely Nerves which ſtrengthens and knits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether the King and People, the People amongſt themſelves, and the whole frame of Government in one firm and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble knot of Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity.</hi> That the Parliaments taking up Arms was to defend onely, to repell the force and violence practiſed by a few of the King's ſide at firſt, afterwards to provide againſt the miſchief which His party heightened through Rage againſt the Parliament, pretence of Loyalty towards the King, might ſeveral ways intend. That the Parliaments re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting His and His Party's attempts, was, as you then judged and diſcourſed, for no other end, then to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their own juſt Priviledges, in order to the Main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the Laws and Liberties of their fellow Subjects: That they did not intend an offenſive War, the conſequences whereof, as of all Civil Diſcords, could not but prove calamitous and ſad, the event and period as fatall and uncertain, when as beſides the two Parties immediately engaged each againſt the other, a middle and Neutrall part, although wiſer in their own eyes then their Fellow Subjects, worſe (as well in the <note n="b" place="margin">See the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> Printed there, <hi>pag.</hi> 26, 27.</note> King's Parties Accompt as in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments)
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:116061:7"/>
would fall in, more to be ſhunned then a moderate Enemy. That it being preſumed the aim and councels of the Parliament and all men elſe being for Peace and Juſtice, a War once waged would hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and deſtroy their ayms, and produce more over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures for diſcord, more freſh ſupplies for quarrelling; in the proſecuting which, many unexpected chances would fall out to increaſe the diſcord, as in the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies between man and man, he who hath not been ſo forward and viſibly active for the ſide unto which he doth adhere, ſhall be traduced and accuſed by him that loves him not, for a Neutrall or an Enemy. That amidſt their hopes of Conquering, there would not be wanting diſcontented and ſeditious humours, even out of their own Party, to traduce and calumniate their proceedings, if not conſonant to their particular humours and phantaſies; That thoſe humours would be fed and animated by the firſt and common Enemy on purpoſe to divide and weaken the prevailing Power: That divers other Conſequences likely to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſult from War, would prove harſh and irkſom to a People born and governed under Laws and Peace, as that the Souldiery and prevailing power, knowing their own opportunity and ſtrength, would be apt to intermeddle with private Intereſts, to the perverting Juſtice and trampling down the Laws, <hi>which in a time of Peace diſtributes to every man his juſt right,</hi> ſo that thereby the People would not only want the bleſſing of Peace, but grow ſubject to the oppreſſion, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and injuries incident to a War. The Parliament could not but foreſee that in caſe a War were to be waged, their own Countrymen, the Engliſh (both Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Common Souldiers) muſt fight it out: For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigners,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116061:7"/>
Souldiers of Fortune when they have gained, will deſiſt their undertakings and be gone. That the Engliſh were unaccuſtomed to war, therefore not fit for the Diſcipline and managing thereof, through an eaſie and ſoft way of breeding not able to endure the hardſhip and duties of a War, howbeit experience hath otherwiſe proved it. That the Engliſh Gallantry and their courage, un-acquainted with the conditions of a Warfare and the temper requiſite to a Souldier, might make them upon every diſcontent as apt to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiny and reſiſt, as fight; for he is not always the beſt Souldier who hath moſt courage, unleſs he hath tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per withall to yeeld obedience to the commands of his Superiours. The Parliament could not but be ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible withall of the troubled condition of their fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Subjects, that the apprehenſion of Engaging would carry with it a ſad aſpect, all men unwilling to, and wary how they did Engage. That the engaging Parties on either ſide when they ſee the face of War inevitably approaching would for their better ſtrength and Union betake themſelves to what Policy, Pacts and Leagues they could, Defenſive and Offenſive, as to binde themſelves and friends by Vow and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant; which being to conſiſt of ſeverall Heads and Parts, could not be ſo exactly and entirely framed, but might admit of a doubtfull ſenſe, how to be be obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, how to be underſtood, in part or in the whole, ſo conſequently divide the Covenanters within them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They could not but withall know, that which ſide ſoever ſhould prevail, both ſides would be looſers, the King and Kingdom vaſt <note n="a" place="margin">See it reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the Declaration Printed at <hi>Oxford</hi> 1643 <hi>pag.</hi> 13.</note> ſufferers in the loſs; as they in an humble &amp; dutiful Meſſage, although contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe interpreted, did in the ſadneſs of their hearts fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116061:8"/>
the King. That in this War, the prevailing power would be to ſeek (to carry an even and well tempered hand) how to deal with the vanquiſhed their own Country-men and miſtaken fellow-Subjects (for 'twas a Miſ-underſtanding which firſt made the rent, Scorn to acknowledge and retract their Errour, widened and continued it) for if they did inflict too heavy a puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, either pecuniary by Mulct or corporall by Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonment, 'twould ſeem unjuſt and harſh from the Conquerour being of their own Nation, and keep off the hopes of reconcilement and re-union: if too gentle and remiſs, 'twould leave and allow the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered a Power &amp; means of recovering their ſtrength again. So that the War, from revenge on the one or from hopes on the other ſide, would continue till all were loſt, or the Conquered perchance become the Conquerours. That there would not want Plots and Stratagems to interrupt and deſtroy their hopes of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing and ſucceſs, as, whileſt they ſate ſolicitous and intentive to their Councels, there would be offered to them Forreign Tenders from abroad, private Addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes here at home, all from the ſame diſ-affected and troubled Fountain, in matters concerning which they haply might have neither Power nor Connuzance, to take up their thoughts and divert their Councels, to retard and hinder their ſucceſs. That, above all, in the doubtfull events of War, as it was likely to fall out <hi>betwixt Perſons offending</hi> on the one part <hi>hating to be Reformed,</hi> and <hi>a Court of Parliament</hi> on the other <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. cap. 25.</note> 
               <hi>choſen and ſet apart to redreſs Grievances in a Common-wealth,</hi> Offenders would apply themſelves for refuge to the King a Supream power, which if He did protect (<note n="b" place="margin">Mr. <hi>John Heywood</hi> on the life of <hi>Hen.</hi> 4.</note> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thereby the Offenders faults His own) would
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:116061:8"/>
without diſpute revert to His Diſhonour, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently beget a Jealouſie and Difference betwixt Him and His People; which if the Parliament ſhould take ill His protecting them, there would iſſue a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt preparatory to a War; Thence if the King en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged and the Parliament reſiſt or fight, They could not hope if they were ſubdued, to avoid the Charge of High-Treaſon, nor think it an eaſie thing in the firſt beginnings of their ſtrength, to prove Conque<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours over a King ſeated a long time in an Ancient Monarchy, inveſted with many advantages of Power and guarded with Courtiers, Friends of all ſorts, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, Favourites, all of which had their Retinue alſo and Train of Friends to aſſiſt, in caſe of needing ſuch. That if the Parliament, notwithſtanding, ſhould pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, they would and muſt to keep up their Power, lay Taxes and Payments on the People, who when the War did but ſeem, or was neer at an end, their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints would be, and they repiningly murmure <hi>[The War is ended, the Taxes and Payments yet continued]</hi> not conſidering, That it is of as great concernment to keep as to gain a Victory, when as the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in caſe of their prevailing were to weigh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all the Doubts and Dangers attending them, the Care Jealouſie and Fears, which no men but would avoid the troubles of, and ſuch as They muſt be ſubject to untill a Conqueſt fully had: the Cares againſt the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſall and Treacheries of their Enemy, the Jealouſie of Friends proving falſe or falling off, the Fears of looſing what they ſhould gain, all theſe being paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive, more penſive and anxious, then the Hopes of the Adverſe Part, Fears more deeply ſeizing and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieting the Conquerour's Spirits (eſpecially whileſt
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116061:9"/>
their Victory is accompanied with ſtudy and thoughts of mercy towards the Conquered) Hopes in the van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhed being more bold and active, raiſing thoughts working ſtill how to recover what they have loſt, That Forreign Enemies as well as home-bred are to be provided againſt, Nor foreſeeing the danger which might befal in caſe the Enemy ſhould regain a Power. That a Conquerour would be held at the beſt but an uſurper for the time. That all Diſaſters and Evils happening, whether as Judgments from above, as Sickneſs, Famine and the like, whether Oppreſsions and wrong doings here on earth, what Enormities and Errours committed or ſuffered either in Church or State, all to be laid to the charge of the preſent Power, which governs and rules no better in the Peoples ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count and murmurings. That thence they reckon all the Diſaſters of the War to flow, not looking on the firſt Occaſion and Authors of the War, That when a Victory ſhall be gained which <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Victoria naturâ inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ba eſt.</hi> Cicero.</note> naturally is proud and inſolent, and by Pride comes Contentions, Emu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Variances in Actions as well as in Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Conquerour's ſtrength would be thereby weakened, and thence in danger to be loſt. That un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till a compleat and totall Conqueſt made, which could not be without much preſſure and heavy ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings on the vanquiſhed, without charge and payments laid on all, Enemies, Friends (Enemies in being Fined for their Delinquency, Friends burthened by reaſon of their Expence and charge in the Publique Service) an Army was to be continued and maintained to prevent Inſurrections here at home, Inroads and Invaſions from abroad. That an Army was to conſiſt of mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titudes of Souldiers, thoſe multitudes would have
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116061:9"/>
their ſeverall humours and opinions tending to Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, conſequently to the deſtruction and ruin of the whole. That without an extraordinaty care to pleaſe and ſatisfie them in their demands, there would be Mutinying, Revolting and Inconſtancy in the common Souldiery, for want of judgement to diſcern for what they fought. That there are to be Agents and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers belonging to and providing for an Army, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers, Expenditors, Treaſurers, others too many to be here recited, who <hi>in troubled Waters</hi> will bring into their private Banck what is to be raiſed for the Publique uſe, or at leaſt the <hi>People jealous will ſurmiſe as much, and that the War and Calamities thereof are protracted through their corruption and privy gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</hi> That if the Conquerour's Power ſhall at any time abate, before a full and totall Conqueſt made, he will be to ſeek what courſe to take to increaſe it again: Forcing and Impreſſing men to fight in a Cauſe ſo intricate (as unto ſome it ſeemed then, and for a long time controverted as this hath been) will prove harſh and irkſom, and will meet with reſiſtance in a People made and born free. That in the Confuſions of a Civil war many Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and Emulations upon true or miſapprehended grounds would fall out amongſt the Orders and Ranks of men, to diſturb and overthrow the Degrees and Dependencies each on other according to their ſeveral &amp; reſpective Qualities, which the Parliament could not but foreſee, and therefore in their Prudence and for the maintenance of the Peace and Vnity, would at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt nothing to the begetting ſuch Strifes or Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders in a Comonwealth. Amongſt the reſt, That Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions and Envyings would in all likelyhood happen
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116061:10"/>
through a Miſconceiving, that <hi>between the Gentry and Nobility on the one ſide</hi> being in the next ranke unto the King, and therefore likely to adhere to Him, and <hi>the Commonalty on the other, ſticking faſt to their native Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties</hi> which the King had of late encroached upon, not ſparing the other's alſo, an Emulation might or would be kindled by the Common Enemy to beget an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Diſtraction and Diviſion between two great Bodies (the Gentry and Nobility on the One, and the Commonalty on the Other ſide) before a deliberate &amp; true examining the miſunderſtanding, which the heat of War would ſcarce give leave unto, ſhould ſet it aright.</p>
            <p>Theſe Reaſons throughly weighted could not but induce the Parliament to decline a war, yea deter Them from leavying one: Theſe might withall, together with many more which might be added hereunto, imprint in you and in all men elſe, who ſhall impartially look into the beginnings and progreſs of this War, an undoubted knowledge of the Parliaments juſt Actings, and theſe Reaſons of Fore-ſight together with what hath paſt, might ſatisfie all knowing and diſcerning men, that if the Parliament did intend to levy a War againſt the King's Evill Counſellours, the Kingdome's <note n="a" place="margin">K. <hi>James</hi> his Speech in Parliament, 1609.</note> 
               <hi>Peſts</hi> and <hi>Vipers</hi> rather Then they would be born down in their juſt defence, They did not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to leavy one againſt the King, who had as many Freinds to adhere unto, as the Parliament had Enemies of many ſorts, Offenders, Intereſted and obnoxious perſons to confront and oppoſe them. But. I may ſpare the pains of ſetting forth what your own Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath foreſeen, and your Actions have thitherto directed you.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:116061:10"/>
For Sir <hi>R. C.</hi> his ſake and yours, rather through the ſame motions of Conſcience, Judgement, many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Gentlemen of quality did take part with ye. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and after his untimely death you carried us on in an active conſtancy, challenging about ſeven years ſince, (when the King began to make <hi>Oxford</hi> a Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon) ſome Travellers of His Party and enquiring whether they went, they confeſſed to <hi>Oxford,</hi> and their errand, You roughly replied <hi>['Twas they and ſuch as they that did take part with the King againſt His Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and People,] [That they did magnifie the King, &amp;c. to beget and foment a War.]</hi> A little before, you with many other Gentlemen of the three neighbouring Counties, did enter into an Aſſociation for a joyntly defending one another. If the Enemy ſhall prevail, whether it will be Treaſon for what is paſt, or made ſo for the time to come, I argue not, but remember well how criminall and Traiterous the King's Friends have reported it. About ſix years ſince, the Enemy grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing powerfull in theſe parts, and <hi>Briſtoll</hi> being gained by Him, you lived within His Quarters, bound by ſtrong obligation not to depart but to be limited to a Summons. The King ſoon after He had taken that City, came thither to compoſe the difference between Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> and the Earl of <hi>Hartford</hi> about the Governourſhip of that Place, He had then amongſt other things, a ſurvey of the Gentlemen dwelling neer and their affections, caſting and examining with His Friends there who might be for, who againſt Him; ſome of His Courtiers undertook for this, ſome for that Gentleman and Neighbour. A great Courtier a Friend of yours undertook or moved His Majeſtie on your behalf, whereunto the King having been belike
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:116061:11"/>
poſſeſſed before with an ill opinion of you, replied with harſh and diſgracefull words, as I have credibly heard, againſt your perſon; which 'tis preſumed He could not charge you with, from any immediate or neer notice He had of you, but as you were repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto Him by ſome who loved you not. He never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, whether out of His indulgence to gain you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to His Party or to Try you after, when He had made ſure His Conqueſt, your name being in the Catalogue of this County Rebels, the <note n="a" place="margin">Lent Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſizes appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to be held at <hi>Tewksbury,</hi> April 11. 1643.</note> Time and Place appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for your Tryall, was content to preſerve you from being undone being then at His mercy: What uſe might be made of His ſparing you, you knew beſt. Two yeers after, <hi>Briſtoll</hi> was got from Him, much of which ſervice attributed unto you, with ſome other Gentlemen of the Neighbourhood, leading up the Countrymen unto the Siege thereof, the Lord Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall then and afterwards giving you applauſe for that your aid. About three years ſince, you cauſed divers Meetings to be had in ſeverall Towns neer unto us, where the Countrymen were ſummoned to declare what Arms they had, whatſoever the pretence was in looking into the Book, which the Pariſhioners do keep for ſuch their Poor as are relievable by a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute-Law, and taking care for them, examining the eſtates of ſuch as were of ability to relieve the Poor, of ſuch as were fit and beſt able to be at the charge of Arms for the repulſing Souldiers, in caſe they came on the ſudden to quarter below-hill or to do other vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, then to return up hill to their friends who might aſſiſt them (ſuch was the condition of theſe and the adjacent parts, where Parties were ſcattered up and down, the Parliament having friends in theſe incloſed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:116061:11"/>
and nearer Parts, the King in the Champeign, and not far diſtant from us) yet you, my ſelf, and the Country<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, knew we had another and more uniform aym of preventing ſudden incurſions, which the King's Party (many of them being Gentlemen and well horſed) might offer unto our Neighbours. Not long after, you were choſen to be our Knight for the County, in the competition of which place, my ſelf, your ſervant, was ſedulous and ſucceſsfull to take off all blemiſhes then thrown on you by thoſe who laboured as much to fill the County-Court with the noyſe of your being for the King. Soon after that, you were challenged by a <note n="*" place="margin">Sir <hi>J. H.</hi>
               </note> fellow-Member ſitting in the Houſe of Parliament, to be within one of the Qualifications which renders men <hi>Delinquents;</hi> Notwithſtanding which, you Sate, Voted, and were Truſted in the Houſe; At ſeverall meetings you enforced ſuch Arguments againſt the King's Party, and for the Parliaments, You have them yet in your breaſt, and can deal at ſingle hand with any of the oppoſite Party, if affection, importunity, and often dropping ſtrange inventions into your ears ſhall not miſleade you, that you ſatisfied the hearers, and even convinced them, had they been convincible. Since that, upon the newly hatched, and eaſie to be reconciled Difference between the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent,</hi> you received a Letter from your above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named Servant, mentioning the probability of the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies advance in or about <hi>July</hi> was twelve moneth, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>London,</hi> in that Letter ſetting forth, <hi>That neither of thoſe two Tenents of</hi> Presbyterian, Independent, <hi>had taken as yet ſuch root, as to beget a quarrell, to the over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of both upon their Conquering,</hi> which I rather think to be an event of their good ſucceſs, then from
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116061:12"/>
any ſelf-wilfull-humour, many of them on either part being ſober and diſcerning Gentlemen, and if through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly weighed, what is like to be the iſſue of this new ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diviſion? That for the diſſentings ſake of three or four Gentlemen (you will not grant that there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny whom you think to have been forward to lead on a Party) for whoſe known valour, whoſe many conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and ſucceſsfull atchievements in this War, bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing yee to this plenitude of Power, you may eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence with them for one puny error in Opinion, that I ſay the People muſt embroyl in a ſecond War, about tearms meerly notionall, about opinions ſtrange and unknown to them: In the firſt War they knew for whom they fought (for the King, or for the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) about a Form of Government, which hath not, nor can take deep root, untill the War, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founds &amp; overthrows all Government, be ended. The direct and certain Iſſue in the Tryall of the Conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was, <hi>Whether the King having by His Creatures actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally invaded the Subject's Liberties</hi> (the other differences in Church and State are collaterall, accidentally emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent out of the grand Difference about the firſt and more principall, the Subject's Liberty:) <hi>The Court of Parliament ſhould ſit as Scepticks, to look on only, without purpoſing, or endeavouring to redreſs the ſame,</hi> or to be confined in their Councels, as their Enemies ſhould preſcribe, or, the extreameſt of all, ſo driven to new Councels, to extraordinary high and ſevere proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, to ſeldom practiſed and unheard of courſes, the paſſages and quality of the Perſons with whom they had to deal, being weighed withall, as where the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe is imminently dangerous, the miſchief deſperate, the Cure muſt be anſwerable, or the whole Body
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:116061:12"/>
periſh for want of a timely and prudent remedy to be applyed. Your actions, Sir, if rigid and ſevere, as to your Enemies, if variable and uncertain, as to your ſelves, may in theſe ſtreights and exigencies whereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Ye are driven and forced for ſafety, be diſpenſed with. It ſeems to fare with Ye, as with Seafaring men in a boyſterous ſtorm, who are feign to ſteer their veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell which way they may beſt ſecure their Fraught and Charge, ſometimes Northerly, ſometimes plain North, ſometimes Northweſt, ſometimes Northeaſt, ſometimes plain South, ſometimes North again, ſo from one croſs point to another, having ſtill the Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and End of their voyage in their eye; So with Ye, encountring with ſuch uncertainty and variety of oppoſitions from your Enemies (yet all meeting in one Center, to the ſubverſion of your Power and ſtrength) ſuch Non-conformity and Diſſention, even amongſt your ſelves and friends, that ye cannot as yet act with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in a direct, certain, and conſtant compaſs, to pleaſe all Lookers on, yet your aym and end may be one and the ſame, the ſupreameſt Law, <hi>the Peoples</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Nulla tam ſancta Lex eſt, quam non op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porteat, ſi ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus Populi po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulet, urgeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas, muta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> Bodin. lib. 4. de Repub.</note> 
               <hi>Safety.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, if ye ſhall fayl, or not able to make good your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings, We know by a ſeven years ſince experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, how barbarouſly and cruelly your Enemies ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice did ſhew it ſelf againſt ye, as being Rebels, in caſe they ſhall recover their Power again, how a deſperate revenge added to, will ſecond their firſt and furious cruelty, and to crown their glory, as for the better exalting their pretence, they ſhall impute it unto Gods juſtice, ſaying <hi>[It is the Lords doing,</hi> it may be his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering it through your Diviſions, <hi>and it is marvellous in our eys</hi> that he hath wreſted the Sword out of our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies hands, and put it into ours, for no man they will
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116061:13"/>
ſay can think that Rebellion ſhall for ever paſs unpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed] Then when they have regained their Power, they will not want Arguments from their own, as from a Neutrall part ſiding with them upon their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quering, to bring whom they pleaſe within the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs of <hi>Treaſon</hi> and <hi>Rebellion,</hi> and to make your <note n="*" place="margin">See your Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, 1647.</note> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and your Acts their ſport and ſcorn, thoſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamations of the King's, lately proſcribing and accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing many of both Houſes of Parliament <hi>guilty of High Treaſon,</hi> with other Edicts of His, to be revived, thoſe Sentences and Judgments ſeriouſly denounced againſt Them and their Proceedings, the Scoffs and Flouts jeſtingly paſſed on ye and your Friends, to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted, and by the Wit and Power of your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries made good againſt ye, when ye have loſt your Power.</p>
            <p>Theſe ſtout and circumſpect wayes of yours are moſt remembred, and deeplyeſt lodged in their breſts who ſpeak leaſt of them<hi>:</hi> I am only the Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brancer, and cannot believe it to be a defection and falling off, as that you think the Parliament and their ſtrength too weak to protect their Members, therefore to forſake it. Your Power is viſible yet, your ſtrength not ſhortned; the great difficulties, the fierce conflicts which ye have wreſtled with, the revolting of your Friends, the multiformity of Opinions amongſt your ſelves, might have abated your ſucceſs, and weakened your ſtrength, had not an Almighty hand ſupported ye amongſt thoſe difficulties. Never ſo many Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gems, Policies, and Falſhoods practiſed by an Enemy to impair your ſtrength, to advance their own, but that the God of Truth hath diſcomfited and diſpelled them all. In which, whether He hath done it in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:116061:13"/>
to the juſtice of your Cauſe, or in His foreknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg of their malice, to be avenged, if they could have got the upper hand, I leave it to the judgment of the cryed up <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. p 263</note> Author, who hath more fitly obſerved <hi>That Gods wiſe Providence often permits what his revealed word approves not,</hi> then he hath ſuited his <hi>reſembling</hi> your <hi>Succeſſes</hi> to <hi>proſperous windes filling the Sayls of Pyrates, to juſtifie their Piracy,</hi> when as the giving or denying Victory and Courage in the day of Battell, is a more immediate and effectuall work of Gods Almighty Power, acting and taking an eſpeciall care in diſpoſing the affairs of War.</p>
            <p>To proceed, and ſhew how petty a difference there is betwixt thoſe two Tenents, is eaſie for any man who ſhall enquire into the quality of either, of what growth, ſettlement, or extent they are; The one (the <hi>Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian)</hi> not ripe enough as yet to be eſtabliſhed, neither the times now fit to entertain a fixt or eſtabliſhed form of Government to binde all ſorts of men: Many having been left at liberty, whether they have or will take the Covenant, many who have taken it, thinking themſelves not obliged forthwith, and in all parts to keep it, having for ſome cauſe diſcovered ſince their taking, ſet it aſide: The other (the <hi>Independent)</hi> a ſeeming, rather then a certain abdication, or a totall renouncing all Government, or for ever. The Lord Generall and his Army (called <hi>Independents,</hi> but why, let them that call them ſo anſwer for it) have ſolemn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <note n="b" place="margin">In their Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance, da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Novem. 1648. pag. 6</note> declared againſt ſuch Diſorder, and Non-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The <hi>Independent</hi> Party, as they are called, may haply deſire to ſhake off that heavy yoke of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which grown through the corruption of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and indulgency of Times into Abuſe, Exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancy,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116061:14"/>
and Oppreſſings, doth gall and heavily preſs their fellow Subjects necks, not by an eaſie or ordinary courſe to be taken off. The Contention, indeed, betwixt thoſe two, <hi>Presbyterian, Independent,</hi> grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as before obſerved, through the pride of conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or cunningly contrived by their common enemy, on purpoſe by dividing to overcome them both.</p>
            <p>The difference in diſpute is not in Opinion but in Fact, as (amongſt other things) unto whoſe charge the deluge of Blood ſpilt in this war is to be laid? Ye have declared That it is to be laid at the King His Parties doors, particularly the bloodguilty and horrid act of hindring the relief of Ireland, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by thouſands of his Proteſtant Subjects have been ſlain, which holdes the three heretofore united King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms, in a languiſhing and mournful Eſtate, even at this day, the one divided againſt the other, and the People of all three deſpairing to enjoy their former Peace, ye inſtancing Firſt <hi>In His ſparingly and too late proclaiming their enemies,</hi> Rebels, <hi>when the Rebellion firſt broke out, by ſigning Commiſsions to the chief Actors in the Rebellion.</hi> The Parliaments Commiſſioners at the <note n="a" place="margin">See the Objections and Anſwers at large in the relation of the paſſages at the meeting at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg</hi> 1644. printed then at <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </note> Treaty of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>xbridg</hi> urging be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, <hi>His diſapproving the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcriptions of the Adventurers and Officers of the Army employed for the relief of his Proteſtant Subjects there, by means whereof the courſe intended was then diverted, His making a Ceſſation with the Rebels, which had it not been made in the time of their greateſt wants, and the Forces employed againſt them not drawn off, they might in probability have been ere this ſubdued, and the war even finiſhed,</hi> in ſtead thereof it is protracted. That Kingdom having been by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116061:14"/>
the proweſs and wiſdom of His <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. <hi>Q Eliz.</hi>
               </note> Predeceſſors kept entire, united unto and a <note n="b" place="margin">The Law Book caſes give the reaſon why the bringing counterfeit mony into England out of Ireland, is but <hi>Miſpriſion of Treaſon,</hi> although the bringers know and ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it. <hi>Quia Hibernia eſt membrum Angliae, Dalton,</hi> Juſtice of Peace in cap. de High Treaſon.</note> Member of this State of England, is by His and His Party's ſtrength abetting it, put into a Condition and even invited to invade and conquer This. That <hi>the Commiſsioners ſent by the two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the better ſupply and encouragement of the Army in that Kingdom, were diſcoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced and commanded from the Councel there, where the proſecution of the war was to be managed: and By whoſe Authority and Command was all this done?</hi> The Houſe of Lords and Commons in the debate with the King about the affaires of <hi>Ireland,</hi> ſent His Majeſty word, that <hi>His meſſage then ſent to Them, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in He chargeth Them with falſe pretences, and a purpoſe in Them to divert large ſummes of money collected from the Engliſh, from the proper uſe to which it was intended, was an high breach of the Priviledge of Parliament, and upon that occaſion They declare many particulars of their care for the relief of Ireland, and the King's hindring it.</hi> Thoſe par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars there expreſſed are as followeth, They declare <hi>That this bloudy Rebellion was firſt vaiſed by the ſame Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells that had before brought two Armies within the bowels of this Kingdom, and two proteſtant Nations ready to welter in each others bloud, which were both defrayed a long time at the charge of the poor Commons of England, and quietly at laſt disbanded by God's bleſsing on the Parliaments endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours. That this deſigne failing, the ſame wicked Councels who had cauſed that impious war, raiſed this barbarous Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion in</hi> Ireland, <hi>and recommended the ſuppreſsing there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (for the better colour) to the Parliaments care, who out</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:116061:15"/>
               <hi>of a fellow-feeling of the unſpeakable miſeries of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Brethren there (not ſuſpecting this horrid Plot, now too apparent) did cheerfully undertake that great work, and do really intend and endeavour to ſettle the Proteſtant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and a permanent Peace in that Realm to the Glory of God, the honor and profit of His Majeſty, and ſecurity of His three Kingdoms. But how they have been diſcouraged, retarded and diverted in and from this pious and glorious work, by thoſe trayterous Councels about his Majeſty, will appear by theſe particulars.</hi> They there mention <hi>the ſending over at firſt of twenty thouſand pounds by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and that good way found out to reduce Ireland by the Adventure of private men, without charging the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject in general, which would probably have brought in a million of money, had the King continued in or neer London, and not by leaving His Parliament, and making war upon it, ſo intimidated and diſcouraged the adventurers, and others who would have adventured, that that good Bill is rendred in a manner ineffectuall.</hi> They mention that <hi>when at the ſole charge of the Adventurers, five thouſand foot, and five hundred horſe were deſigned for the relief of</hi> Munſter, <hi>under the Command of an Engliſh Lord, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was wanting but a Commiſsion to inable him for the ſervice, ſuch was the power of wicked Councel, that no Commiſsion could be obtained from the King, by reaſon whereof</hi> Lymrick <hi>was wholy loſt, and the Province of</hi> Mun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>ſince in very great diſtreſs.</hi> That <hi>when wel-affected per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons at their own charge by way of Adventure had prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red twelve Ships and Pinaces, with a thouſand Land Forces for the ſervice of Ireland, deſiring nothing but a Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion from His Majeſty, that Commiſsion, after twice ſending to</hi> York <hi>for it, and the ſhips lying ready to ſet ſail three weeks together, at the charge of neer three hundred pounds</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116061:15"/>
               <hi>a day, was likewiſe denied, and thoſe Adventurers (rather then to loſe their Expedition) were conſtrained to go by vertue of an Ordinance of both Houſes of Parliament. That although the Lords luſtices of Ireland earneſtly deſired to have two Pieces of Battery ſent over, as neceſſary for that ſervice, yet ſuch commands were given to the</hi> Officers of the Tower, <hi>That none of the King's Ordnance muſt be ſent to ſave His Kingdom.</hi> That a <hi>prime Engineer and Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termaſter-General of the Army in Ireland, and in actual em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment there againſt the Rebels, was called away from that important ſervice by expreſs command from the King, That a Captain, Controller of the Artillery, a man in pay and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally employed and truſted here by the Lord Lieutenant of Ireland, for providing and ordering the Trayn of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, which was to be ſent to Dublin, and who had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived great ſummes of money for that purpoſe, was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded from that employment and truſt, to ſerve the King in this unnatural war againſt His Parliament, and when the Parliament had provided ſix hundred ſuits of Clothes for preſent relief of the poor Souldiers in Ireland, and ſent them towards Cheſter, the Waggoners that undertook the carriage of them were aſſaulted by the King's Souldiers lying about Coventry, who took away the Clothes. That three hundred ſuits of Clothes ſent likewiſe by the Parliament for Ireland with a Chirurgion's cheſt of Medicaments towards Cheſter, were all taken away by the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s Troopers un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der command of a Captain, together with the Carrier's horſes and Waggon, for the King's ſervice.</hi> As likewiſe that <hi>a great number of draught-horſes prepared by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament for the Artillery and baggage of the Iriſh Army, and ſent to Cheſter for that purpoſe, being there attending a paſſage, were then required by the King for His preſent ſervice in England, whoſe Forces were ſo quartered about</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116061:16"/>
               <hi>the Roads to</hi> Ireland, <hi>that no Proviſion could paſs thither by Land with any Safety.</hi> That <hi>two other Captains, the Admiral and vice. Admiral, of the Ships appointed to lie upon the Coaſt of</hi> Ireland <hi>to annoy the Rebels, and to prevent the bringing Ammunition and relief from For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Parts, were both called away from that Imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the King's Command, and by reaſon of their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture from the Coaſt of</hi> Munſter, <hi>to which they were de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned, the Rebels there have received Powder, Ammu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition and other relief from Forreign Parts.</hi> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">See theſe Charges mentioned by the Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment againſt the King, in Mr. <hi>May</hi> his Hiſtory <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 118.</note> By which particulars (ſay they) it may ſeem, that <hi>thoſe Rebels were countenanced there, upon deſign, to aſsiſt the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the Parliament here, eſpecially conſidering that thoſe confident Rebels have preſumed very lately to ſend a Petition to the King, intituling themſelves,</hi> His Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Catholick Subjects of IRELAND, <hi>and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaining of the Puritan Parliament of</hi> England, <hi>and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firing that ſince His Majeſtie comes not thither according to their expectation, they may come into</hi> England <hi>to His Majeſtie;</hi> So the Queſtion by way of Argument be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the King and Parliament, as between the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsioners on either ſide, is laid aſide, and now to be decided by no other Umpire then the Sword, and what the two oppoſite Parties on either ſide have a long time ſtrove for (the one defending their Cauſe in their Books and Writings by vehemency and height of Wit, the other theirs by ſolid and ſubſtantiall Prudence) is left to the Conquerour to determine.</p>
            <p>What the odds is betwixt their Writings, becauſe controverted by either ſide, which Party doth declare and argue the more Prudentially the reaſons of their ſeverall undertakings in this quarrell, as which Party, (the Kings or the Parliaments) have writ more ſolidly
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116061:16"/>
and ſubſtantially concerning the Subject of this War, which more genuinely and ſincerely without expatia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting or rayling Jeſts have argued, let the impartiall Reader judg. So becauſe there may not want fuell for Contention, 'tis debated concerning the Actions of Cruelty on either part (the Kings, the Parliaments) which did act with more cruelty, by putting to the Sword, ſpayling, by conſuming with Fire, laying waſte Towns, Villages, Houſes. I believe our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour <note n="a" place="margin">BERK<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SHIRE, and other places neer us.</note> County, as far as you and I have obſerved, gives Teſtimony againſt the One in a ſad Record. As to the Writings on either ſide, for Inſtance ſake take three or four here following for the reſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Letter to the Governour and Councell of War at <hi>BRISTOL</hi> (that City being then a Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for the Parliament) from the Lord Generall of the King's Forces <note n="b" place="margin">See Mr. <hi>May</hi> his Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the Parliament of England, mentioning the Demand and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</note> 
               <hi>requiring the Governour and Councell there to forbear the putting to death the two Citizens,</hi> threatning withall <hi>to retaliate the like Judgment and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution upon ſome Gentlemen of the Parliaments Party, kept Priſoners by the King's,</hi> with the Reſolution, and ſober Anſwer of the Governour and Councell to ſuch Meſſage. The quality of which Anſwer is fore-judged already, and Replyed unto in Print, <hi>To be an inſolent</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">In a Book of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, called the <hi>States Martyr.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Pamphlet,</hi> with other words of ſcorn, when other men well ſeen in Morals, and the Martiall affairs of War, deem it to be a ſtout, appoſite, and well penn'd Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Secondly, That from the Marqueſſe of <hi>Argyle,</hi> and Sir <hi>William Armyne,</hi> Commiſſioners from both King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of England, Scotland; <hi>fully</hi> 
               <note n="d" place="margin">See the Meſſage and the Anſwer.</note> 
               <hi>and in few words de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering their Intentions and Reaſons for the Summons</hi> ſent to the Governour of <hi>Carliſle;</hi> a Garriſon for the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116061:17"/>
King, with his Anſwer unto them, <hi>full of words, preg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancy of wit, and jealouſie,</hi> rejecting their Summons: And ſome of His Party derogating elſwhere from the worth of <note n="a" place="margin">See the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of the King's af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs in <hi>Scotland,</hi> &amp;c. Where the Hiſtorian ſpeaking of <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> and the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyle,</hi> the Generals of the two oppoſite Armies in the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> he highly extols <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> and as much reviles and derogates from <hi>Argyle,</hi> rendring him in many paſſages of that Book, a poor-ſpirited Souldier, and a Knave, when as in other mens judgments he hath proved himſelf a valiant and expert Commander, a Religious and wiſe Gentleman.</note> one of the Commiſſioners.</p>
            <p>
               <note n="b" place="margin">See this mentioned in the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration of the Lords and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford, March</hi> 1643. and Printed there.</note> A third, Which becauſe 'tis ſhort, You have here recited in the very words, ſent from both Houſes of Parliament to the King, with His Parties deſcant and ſcornful Comment on the ſame.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Meſſage ſent from both Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the King.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>May it pleaſe your Majeſtie,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> Aſſembled in the Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> taking into our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration a Letter ſent from Your Majeſtie, dated the third of <hi>March</hi> inſtant, and directed to the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> of Parliament Aſſembled at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> (Which by the Contents of a Letter from the Earl of <hi>Forth,</hi> unto the Lord General, the Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> we conceive was intended to our Selves) Have reſolved with the concurrent advice, and conſent of the Commiſsioners of the Kingdom of <hi>Scotland,</hi> to repreſent to your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie</hi> in all humility and plainneſſe, as followeth:</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>That,</hi> as we have uſed all means for a juſt, and a ſafe Peace; ſo will we never be wanting to do our utmoſt for the procuring thereof: But when we conſider the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsions
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116061:17"/>
in that Letter of Your <hi>Majeſties,</hi> We have more ſad and deſpairing thoughts of attaining the ſame, then ever; becauſe thereby, thoſe Perſons now Aſſembled at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> who contrary to their duty have deſerted Your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, are put into an equall Condition with it: and this Parliament, Convened according to the known and Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damental Laws of the Kingdom (the continuance whereof is eſtabliſhed by a Law conſented unto by Your <hi>Majeſty)</hi> is in effect denied to be a Parliament: The Scope, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Letter being, to make proviſion how all the Members (as is pretended) of both Houſes, may ſecurely meet in a full and free Convention of Parliament; whereof no other concluſion can be made, but that this preſent Parliament is not a full nor free Convention; And that to make it a full and free Convention of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, the preſence of thoſe is Neceſſary, who, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding that they have deſerted that great <hi>Truſt,</hi> and do Levy War againſt the Parliament, are pretended to be Members of the two Houſes of Parliament.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>And hereupon,</hi> we think our ſelves bound to let Your <hi>Majeſtie</hi> know, That ſeeing the continuance of this Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament is ſetled by a Law (which as all other Laws of Your Kingdoms, Your <hi>Majeſtie</hi> hath ſworn to maintain, as we are ſworn to our Allegiance to Your <hi>Majeſtie,</hi> thoſe obligations being reciprocall) we muſt in duty, and accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly are reſolved with our Lives and Fortunes, to defend and preſerve the <hi>Juſt Rights, and full Power of this Parliament:</hi> And do beſeech Your <hi>Majeſtie</hi> to be aſſured, That your <hi>Majeſties</hi> Royall and hearty Concurrence with us herein, will he the moſt effectuall, and ready means of procuring a firm and laſting <hi>Peace</hi> in all Your <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties</hi> Dominions, and of begetting a perfect underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding between Your <hi>Majeſty</hi> and Your <hi>People;</hi> without
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:116061:18"/>
which Your <hi>Majeſties</hi> moſt earneſt Profeſsions, and our moſt reall Intentions concerning the ſame, muſt neceſſari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be fruſtrated. And in caſe Your <hi>Majeſties</hi> three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms ſhould by reaſon thereof, remain in this ſad and bleeding Condition, tending, by the continuance of this unnaturall <hi>War,</hi> to their <hi>Ruine,</hi> Your <hi>Majeſty</hi> cannot be the leaſt, nor the laſt ſufferer. God in his goodneſs incline Your Royall breaſt, out of Pity and Compaſsion to thoſe deep ſufferings of Your Innocent People, to put a ſpeedy, and happy iſſue to theſe deſperate Evils, by the joynt advice of both Your Kingdoms, now happily united in this <hi>Cauſe,</hi> by their late ſolemn <hi>League</hi> and <hi>Covenant.</hi> Which as it will prove the ſureſt remedy; ſo is it the earneſt prayer of your <hi>Majeſties</hi> Loyall Subjects, the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> Aſſembled in the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Grey <hi>of</hi> Wark, <hi>Speaker of the Houſe of Peers in Parliament</hi> pro tempore. William Lenthall <hi>Speaker of the Commons-Houſe in Parliament.</hi>
                     </signed> 
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Weſtminſter the</hi> 
                        <date>9. <hi>of of</hi> March, 1643.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <head>The Kings Parties Apprehenſion and Comment on the Letter, in theſe words:</head>
                  <p>Whoſoever conſiders that this ſhould be a Letter from Subjects, might well think it very unbeſeeming Language in them to call His Majeſtie's earneſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours for Peace but <hi>Profeſsions,</hi> and their own feigned pretences, <hi>moſt reall Intentions,</hi> but much more won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116061:18"/>
at that menacing Language, that <hi>His Majeſtie cannot be the leaſt, or laſt ſufferer;</hi> which expreſsions from Subjects in Arms to their Soveraign, what dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous conſtruction they may admit, We are unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to mention. Thus much for the King's Parties Comment on the Letter.</p>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>One other intercourſe of Meſſages between both Parties of a latter time. <note n="*" place="margin">See the King's Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter <hi>March</hi> 23. 1644. and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer to the Committees Summons in <hi>April</hi> fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</note> 
               <hi>The Summons ſent by the Committee of both Kingdoms to the Governour of</hi> Newark <hi>for ſurrendring that Town and Fort.</hi> The Summons ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſsing perſwaſive and valid reaſons to ſurrender it, the Governour, rather his Secretaries Anſwer, full of good Language, courage and ſtrength of wit, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in mentioning the King's Parties Letter ſent the 23. of <hi>March</hi> 1644. unto both Houſes of Parliament, he ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges the King's granting gracious Conditions, and proves it, in that He would <hi>Disband His Forces, Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mantle His Garriſons,</hi> &amp;c. He who penned the Anſwer recites not all the King's Propoſals, as that He would have <hi>His Friends Pardoned, the Sequeſtration taken from off their Eſtates,</hi> and the like; either he ſaw not the King's whole Letter, being he recites one part only, or elſe he ſmiles in his ſleeve, thinking by his reſerved and ſhort Comment on His Letter to ſatisfie the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee there, and the whole Kingdom beſides, of the King's gratious inclination in that Letter, whereof the Anſwerer reciteth but one part. The Letter was full and eaſie to be underſtood, taking it collectively and altogether, not apart, as of <hi>Disbanding, Diſmant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, &amp;c.</hi> had not He expected to <hi>have his Friends par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, and their Sequeſtrations wholy taken off.</hi> Such manner of collective ſpeaking is conditional, the one to be done on the one ſide, if the reſt be performed
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116061:19"/>
on the other. The Anſwerer's mentioning ſo much of the Letter as may ſerve the turn, in reciting the King's <hi>gracious promiſe,</hi> leaves out on what Condition the Promiſe is made, the condition annexed to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, fruſtrates the vertue of the Promiſe, for that which the Anſwerer cals <hi>gracious</hi> in the King's Letter of <hi>Disbanding His Forces,</hi> if nothing elſe were to be expected, are in every mans judgment, as in the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerer's, <hi>gracious</hi> indeed, but that the King expects to have <hi>His Friends, His party pardoned, the Sequeſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons wholly taken off from their Eſtates,</hi> were by gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving way to the revoking their own Judgements, to accuſe themſelves of injuſtice-doing, to put them whom the Parliament accounted offenders and their Enemies, into as good or better condition then their own friends: the Anſwerer, if knowing the King's whole Letter, and would contract it into parts, reci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting only that which ſerves his turn, the Committee being preſumed ſolid and underſtanding Gentlemen, would queſtionleſs follow the Dictates of their own Judgment, without replying to the Anſwerer.</p>
            <p>For Oratory and ſtrength of wit, which haply may delight ſome Readers, but cures not the Diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and Calamities of a Civill War, nor ſatisfies the ſerious expectation of unbyaſſed Spectators or Actors in theſe Tragedies; it is confeſs'd, that the Aſſembly at <hi>Oxford</hi> &amp; their Party in their Quarters there, having the more facete and nimble wits, with the help and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence of the Youth and Schollars there, may ſeem to exceed the Parliament and thoſe whom the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment imploys in their Empreſsions, But let the Books on either ſide be examined by the Teſt of Reaſon, Prudence, the Reader will ſoon diſcern the Difference:
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116061:19"/>
And theſe four remarkable Meſſages inſtanced in, may decide the Conteſt, none other of all their Conflicts of that kinde being more oppoſite each to other, nor any of their Meſſages reciprocally ſent, more diſdainfully rejected on either ſide (as far as I have traced their Writings) then theſe four above-mentioned.</p>
            <p>But to the Reaſons of your deſerting your firſt judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, if ſo you have, I rather judg it to be a fencing and tryal of wits in an Argumentative way of diſcourſing only, then any ſettled revolting from your firſt Opinion: you are well read in the good man's Character, <hi>who will not be afraid for any evill tydings, His heart ſtandeth faſt, and will not ſhrink, &amp;c.</hi> The Arguments you have lately taken up againſt the reſiding part of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and the Army, the maintainer of your Power, &amp; next under God the preſerver of our Peace, are none of yours, nor like to yours. The Houſe of Parliament being grown thin; By your, and other Gentlemen of your Eminency deſerting it, is become more thin; the more weak it is through your Defections, the more need it hath of being ſupported by your Return. As for the <hi>Force</hi> which you and your ſubdivided party urge <hi>to be offered</hi> to ye <hi>by the Army</hi> your Servants, <hi>an high affront and breach of Parliament Priviledges,</hi> Both your parties, <hi>Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Independent</hi> ſeem to be forced alike, not in an equall degree of Strength and Number, but in a ſtrict and cloſer tye of Policy and Prudence, by and through an extream and inevitable Neceſſity to the preſervation of Ye and your Friends. Neither you nor any of your Party can deviſe or act a means how to ſettle ſuch a courſe as may prevent a totall confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or the overthrow of thoſe who have already pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed by the. Sword, nor to Still the common Enemy
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116061:20"/>
and Avenger: But if He being hard-driven, ſhall by Treaty or other unſafe way of ſetling a Peace, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vail, He is left at liberty to do His pleaſure. In Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles or like wayes of Parleance, what Security can He give or will He keep, commenſurate to the ſafety and welfare of many thouſands engaged in this Quarrel, to the avoidance of thoſe Dangers and Jealouſies al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready adminiſtred by Him? Within theſe three years you inſtanced <hi>Hen.</hi> 3. His complyance and Signing Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, which when He had by that recovered His Power again, kept none of them. But to your Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and your paralelling <hi>the King's offering a Force to ſix of the Houſes of Parliament,</hi> to <hi>the Force is offered you.</hi> He might peradventure, and by an uſurped Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority do it, to exerciſe a Regall Power above the Laws, from aſſuming unto Himſelf an unlimited and ſtrong conceit of His Soveraignty &amp; Tranſcendency of Might in nothing to be reſiſted, to awe and force this preſent Parliament, and all future Parliaments (in caſe He had any purpoſe to convene any more) to His beck, as 'tis probable. Not long after, by the like me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacing and imperious act of Proclaiming thoſe Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men Traytors, who either obeyed not, or refuſed to conform to His preſent Will; There was no neceſſity but His ſole Will to force all thoſe who complyed not with Him to ſave and reſcue His Creatures from the hand of Juſtice. And whether there be not now a ſtronger neceſſity then before the great and univerſall Engagement of many good and deſerving men, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to you. Sir, In that you take it ill That your <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants</hi> (ſo the Army ſtyle themſelves) <hi>ſhould force their Maſters.</hi> They are not ſimply and preciſely Servants immediate, ſubordinate rather, many of Them your
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116061:20"/>
Equals, Commanders and Officers in the Army, the common-Souldiery commanded and led by Them; Or the Army relatively unto ye as Jurors in a triall of Aſſize before a number of Judges (for ſo ye are, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the reſemblance holds not adequately, as to an Army, and to a Jury.) Let a Major part of Judges in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cline or direct which way they pleaſe: Yet an upright Jury will finde according to the Evidence in being. The Evidence in this caſe is the certainty of knowing and re-collecting things paſt, the foreſight of things to come, which induceth them to bring in ſuch Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict as may render all things Juſt and Safe: for when it ſhall happen to be debated <hi>which ought to be preferred, the Priviledg of Parliament, or the Safety of a Kingdom,</hi> every one can judg which ought to ſway the ballance. Again, admit the Army to be your Servants (yet pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly they are Servants unto thoſe from whom they receive their pay, that is, from the Kingdom, neither from the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> nor <hi>Independent</hi> Party) In a mixt and joynt-Government where more then One com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth, and a mutuall conſent had betwixt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, that the Servants ſhall obey the diſcreeter Party, as between a Maſter and a Miſtreſſe in a Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they mutually conſent that their Family ſhall be directed by the wiſer of the two, there it is left to the election and diſcretion of the Family, which of them (Maſter or Miſtreſſe) to pay obedience unto. It skils not in a Governing and Politique Body (conſiſting of many Ruling, &amp; all conſenting in the main) which is the Major part, unleſs that Major part will do the whole work themſelves, without the help of thoſe whom they do employ: which of them is to be obeyed? That Part rather which Acts and Endeavours (with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:116061:21"/>
reſpect had to the Majority) in the more prudent, watchfull and ſafe way. So 'tis no Diſobedience or Affront offered by your Army, where Obedience may be dangerous to the Obeyours, to your Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and your adherents. For whereas ſome of the King's Party prefer the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> before the <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dependent,</hi> ſome the <hi>Independent</hi> before the <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian,</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">See the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>p.</hi> 224.</note> hating both, yet giving good words un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and complying with the more diſcontented and weaker Party, untill by their cunning Artifice they overcome them alſo; ſo in this <hi>Leger de main,</hi> and ſleight of wit blow the coals of Diſſention betwixt ye both, Ye of the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> can look for no other then <hi>Polyphemus</hi> his courteſie, to be of thoſe laſt to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured. Beſides, as to <hi>the Major or Minor part of Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers ſitting in the Houſe, or ſecluded, or voluntarily abſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves from the Houſe, ſo that the greater number are abſent,</hi> as you reckon: Take heed of that objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, leſt you open an old wound (long ſince ſalved up through God's bleſſing on your ſucceſs) and that Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection be made uſe of againſt ye all of both Houſes, and againſt that Authority whereby Ye have at any time acted ſince the Contention firſt began betwixt the King's Parties claim to their Parliament at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and the Parliaments Parties claim to theirs at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi> For if the King's Party did rightly calculate their numbers which were in both Houſes of Lords and Commons <note n="b" place="margin">See their Declaration Printed at <hi>Oxford March</hi> 1643. towards the end of the Book.</note> 258. either perſonally ſitting at <hi>Oxford,</hi> or occaſionally abſent upon imployment for the King, That number exceeded that of thoſe ſitting at <hi>Weſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter:</hi> ſo that the Argument for the major part of the number of Members <hi>Presbyterially</hi> affected, &amp; that way Covenanted, againſt which the King's Friends have
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116061:21"/>
learnedly, as yet unanſweredly <note n="*" place="margin">In a Book ſtiled <hi>[The preſent Judgment of the Convocation at</hi> Oxford <hi>dated</hi> June 1647.] Which if weighed with the Arguments in the late Letter written by the <hi>London</hi> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to the Lord <hi>Fairfax</hi> and his Councell of War, dated <hi>Jan.</hi> 1648. in behalf of the Covenant and the keeping it, the Reader will ſoon diſcern the odds.</note> argued, is no ſafe or prudent Argument at this time to be uſed, however abetted and ſeconded by an elaborate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly written Letter by the Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don Miniſters, leſt ye help your firſt and common Enemy to rowſe an Objection which hath a long time ſlept, for maintaining their Parliament at <hi>Oxford.</hi> For, by the way, had thoſe Miniſters employed their pains in anſwering that Book, their Letter might have been better credited, and more univerſally received. They much inſiſt on the Proteſtation, taken <hi>May</hi> 1641. wherein the Proteſting is <hi>For the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the King's Honor, Perſon, and Eſtate:</hi> yet the End (at which all matters of weight do aym) is the preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of <hi>Religion, Laws, &amp; Liberties.</hi> The maintenance of the <hi>King's Honor,</hi> &amp;c. is but a piece of the Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; the ſum, full ſenſe &amp; ſcope thereof, the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Religion,</hi> &amp;c. The drift of one of the Grecian wiſe men's advice was <hi>[Reſpice finem]</hi> &amp; the prudential Proverb is (made good by an acute Epigram) <hi>Non refert quà, ſed quò:</hi> So the maintenance of the King's Honor, &amp;c. are but the Means in relation &amp; order to the End, the preſervation of Religion, Laws, &amp;c. The well-weighing which Proteſtation might have confined and ſettled the unreſolved and doubtfull thoughts of man, in what the end and aym of the Proteſtation was, A promiſe to fulfil, in as much as in us lies, the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements of the firſt and ſecond Table of the Law, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>recting our duty towards God and Man, the ſeverall parts in the Proteſtation tending in the ſumme to the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116061:22"/>
maintenance of God's Honor, the King's, the Subjects Right and Liberty, no one part thereof, if rightly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed and underſtood, croſſing another: and therefore how it comes to paſſe, that the Proteſtation being one and the ſame, the courſe of mens affections ſhould be thus divided into Factions, and Part-takings, or that ſome ſhould be of opinion, That <hi>to maintain the King's Honour, Perſon and Eſtate, is to adhere unto Him in this preſent War in what He ſhall command.</hi> They ſhould withall conſider the other parts of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtation <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Defence of the Proteſtant Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the Power and Priviledges of Parliament, the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject's Right and Liberty; for by the Proteſter's ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving all, the King is beſt obſerved and trulieſt, His Honour and Promiſes being engaged to maintain the latter three; when as every one who took the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation did in his thoughts endeavour and intend ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his Power to make Him a Soveraign Lord of a Free and Flouriſhing People, the King's Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations concurring with, and tending to that end: So the Proteſtation taken altogether is beſt obſerved and kept. To the Proteſtation for <hi>the defence of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion,</hi> every one who takes it is not imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately and ſpecially bound by vertue of his Vow to diſcover and make known, to extirpate or remove all Papiſts (that is above the Power and Liberty of every common perſon) neither is wiſhing well alone, and ſitting ſtill a ſufficient diſcharge of the Proteſter's duty of vowing to <hi>Endeavour.</hi> Endeavouring is a progreſſive motion, and the Proteſter's ſupine failing to endeavour, can be no better reckoned of, then the <note n="*" place="margin">Livy.</note> Hiſtorian did of thoſe Souldiers who dreamed of their Enemies, <hi>Votis &amp; ſedendo debellari poſſe,</hi> or what
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116061:22"/>
the <note n="*" place="margin">Iſaiah.</note> Prophet doth of the Egyptians, that <hi>their ſtrength was ſitting ſtill.</hi> A perfunctory and neutrall ſlackneſs in the Proteſter, ſatisfies not the precept which God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf enjoyns, <hi>When thou voweſt a vow unto the Lord, thou ſhalt not be ſlack to pay it,</hi> and wherein many have not onely deſerted this their Vow, but endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured againſt the ſame; others contemplatively only and remiſs as not endeavouring at all, but with cautious reſervations and forbearances keep off their endeavourings. The paſſive and faint obſerving of the Vow in ſome, the Acting contrary to their Vow in others, is a ſin which God is juſtly angry for, viſiting this Land of late with long and heavy judgments; wherefore if he who hath taken this Proteſtation, and ſhall ſolemnly obſerve the ſame, ſhall foreſee, or hath cauſe of ſuſpition to believe, that the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> is, or was when he took the ſame, in danger of declining, &amp; that the Papiſt is connived at &amp; coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenanced by <note n="b" place="margin">Which is not the Author's Obſervation alone, but the unanimous judgment of moſt part of the Kingdom obſerved by their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Petitions at that time preſented, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially that of the Gentry and Trained Bands of the County of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> preſented to their Lord Lieutenant the Earl of <hi>Warwick.</hi> See Mr. <hi>May</hi> his Hiſtory, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 6. <hi>pag.</hi> 105.</note> higher Powers (for the Queſtion is not about the certain and actual bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in of <hi>Popery,</hi> but touching the pregnancy of ſuſpition) if the Proteſter adhereth to that Party which promiſeth to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the Proteſtant, and oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth that which countenanceth the Popiſh, his Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is then trulieſt kept; a Promiſe or Vow, the more purſued, the more fulfilled. In like manner to the other part of the ſame Proteſtation <hi>(viz.) The Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Kings Honour,</hi> every one who takes the ſame is not thereby bound to comply, aſſent unto, and obey the King in whatſoever He may command, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116061:23"/>
unlawfull or unjuſt, or to think all his attempts and actions <hi>Juſtifyable</hi> throughout. This were indeed, in the higheſt degree to honour Him; but in a more ſerious and as truly a Loyall way of His being Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured by His Subjects, is when they or thoſe who are put in Place and Authority over them, ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire into and provide againſt all things incident to His Diſhonour, when they ſhall endeavour to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs all Affronts which may be offered to His Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; This though a more remote and leſs flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, yet a more ſtable and certain diſcharge of Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in Honouring Him. Again, as to that part of the Covenant <hi>[That They had then no intention to diminiſh His juſt Power and Greatneſs]</hi> They might intend no leſs, untill They ſaw They could not overcome Him by humble Applications and Addreſſes, that they could not diſcern any acknowledgment of His former Errours, any placable or propitious heart to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards His Parliament and People; any condiſcend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to thoſe Propoſitions, as the only and neceſſary means for ſetling a ſafe Peace, long ſince tendered to Him joyntly and unanimouſly by ye all, <hi>Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> as they are called (yet not all of ye concluding or providing what was to be done in caſe He did refuſe) But inſtead thereof (contrary to the <note n="*" place="margin">See the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of the large Treaty Pag. 16. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand 4. granted by the King, <hi>Aug.</hi> 1641.</note> Articles of the large <hi>Treaty</hi> agreed upon (viz.) <hi>That none ſhould be admitted to his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell or Attendance but ſuch as ſhould be approved of by both Kingdoms)</hi> gracing and preferring to His neereſt ſecrecy and truſt, a Perſon proclaimed guilty of High Treaſon, charging ſtill and banding with the Parliament, the Supreameſt and greateſt Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell for Weight and Number in all EUROPE, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:116061:23"/>
               <hi>to lay the Blood ſpilt in this War at their doors, and theirs alone,</hi> ever ſeeking by His Pyoners, by a covert and reſtleſs ill-will, one way againſt the <note n="a" place="margin">See the Book called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>pag.</hi> 23. and elſewhere in that Book, His Party's conſtant and continued ill-will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the City of <hi>London.</hi> The City ſtyled by His party, in their wonted Invectives againſt it, <hi>The Nurſery and Treaſury of Armes and Ammunition em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed againſt their King,</hi> continued even to this day to be termed by them <hi>a Rebellious City upon all occaſions,</hi> Mercur. Pragmat. from <hi>Jan.</hi> 28. to <hi>Feb.</hi> 4. 1649. further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuing his Invectives againſt the City in his weekly Pamphlet.</note> Place re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving Them, another a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <note n="b" place="margin">See their Declaration printed at <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> 1643. <hi>pag.</hi> 14, 15. againſt the ſuggeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed irregular and undue proceedings of the Common Councel in <hi>London,</hi> the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentative of the whole City.</note> Friends aſſiſting Them, to undermine their Power. They thought <hi>the Covenant not like an</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">See the Letter of the Miniſters within the Province of <hi>London,</hi> and their notice-taking of the Parliament and Army's con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipt had of the Covenant, <hi>pag.</hi> 8.</note> 
               <hi>Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack out of date,</hi> as the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſmilingly object, but like an Obligation, where the <hi>Obligor</hi> is deſtitute and left remedileſs through the <hi>Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligee</hi> his reſtleſs fury and op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion, diſabling him from performing his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions. <note n="d" place="margin">See His Party's Opinion of the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and the taking it, in the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>pag.</hi> 113, 114, 115. whither and how far it is to be kept, how little uniformity there is in the taking or keeping it, and for what purpoſe in the Author's judgment framed at firſt, how ambiguous and hard to to underſtood, how much miſtaking or diſſembling in the making it at firſt, or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>repreſenting by thoſe who like it not, that howbeit one part thereof is <hi>[That <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> had then no intention to diminiſh the King's <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> Power and Greatneſs]</hi> the Author in the King's name conceives, <hi>That it was made and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the King,</hi> as in many places of the Treatiſe againſt the Covenant he complaineth. See alſo the King's De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, ſince the Pacification, againſt the Scots and the Covenant, <hi>pag</hi> 8. Which Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of his ſee confirmed in the Marqueſſe of <hi>Montroſſe</hi> his Declar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſet forth 1649. as in a Book called the Hiſtory of the King's affaires in Scotland, before recited <hi>pag.</hi> 5.</note> One part of the Covenant then taken, was, That <hi>They had no thoughts or intentions to diminiſh the King's juſt Power and Greatneſs,</hi> Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther part was (when They preſs the Covenant taking, the maintenance of the Peace and Union between the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms) <hi>They would bring to juſtice all</hi> without reſpect of Perſons <hi>who did or ſhould wilfully oppoſe</hi>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:116061:24"/>
               <hi>the ſame, or hinder ſuch Peace and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion.</hi> So that if the King did by Himſelf, by His Friends and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers by His example awing other men from ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the Covenant, or did by any Power or Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, whether to defend Himſelf, or to offend His op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites, act or abet, whereby the Peace became diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turbed, one Kingdom engaged againſt another, the Parliament could not according to their Covenant <hi>preſerve His Power and Greatneſs,</hi> and <hi>puniſh ſuch with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out</hi> reſpect of perſons as <hi>did wilfully oppoſe the ſame,</hi> comprehending all who did adhere unto, or take part with him: So that the Covenant, the parts where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſeem to be inconſiſtent and irreconciliable within themſelves, and therefore not perfectly and exactly to be kept, is either newly to be molded, or (which is more probable) the War to continue between the Covenanters, and the non-Covenanters: many thouſands of men neither having, nor through the King's example willing to take the ſame. The great Quarrel of ignorant men againſt the uniform current of the Holy Scripture, of an higher concernment then an humane Covenant, is acutely taken up by a learned <note n="*" place="margin">Paraus.</note> Writer, <hi>Diſtingue tempora &amp; reconciliantur Scripturae,</hi> in anſwer unto thoſe, who cavil againſt the Scriptures as if the Texts thereof were diſſonant and repugnant each to other, as if God's word, certain and infallible in it ſelf, were contradictory to it ſelf. Diſtinguiſh between the time of the Covenant taking, four or five yeers before the time of bringing the King to Tryal, Obſerve the limitation in the particle of the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant <hi>[That They had then no intention to diminiſh the King's</hi> juſt <hi>Power]</hi> in oppoſition to <hi>unlawful and arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary,</hi> and you will finde that the Covenant could not
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:116061:24"/>
be ſo well and ſafely taken, or that it is not ſo hainouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly broke as your Enemies give out. But to your Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt the Army, That in adhering unto them, is <hi>to truſt to an Arm of Fleſh,</hi> ſo all ſublunary and earthly Powers are but Arms of fleſh. Secondly, <hi>That Independency admits of all Irreligion, Hereſies,</hi> &amp;c. The Propoſition is not well proved, in that ſome particular ſoldiers belonging to, or others well-wiſhing to the Army, do deviſe and publiſh ſtrange and unſound Tenents and Opinions, which is not to be imputed to the Army or the Parliament, neither is a preſent Cure to be applyed for redreſs thereof in all parts and places where they are vented. The Army and their Party have enough to do to prevent and provide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Power and Policy of their Enemies, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an overhaſty endeavoring to ſuppreſs the Schiſms and Errors of every one of their Adherents. The com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint againſt Hereſies &amp; Schiſms abounding, is juſt &amp; ſeaſonable, and the Hereſies moſt fit to be ſuppres'd. The Complaint is made long ſince, and it was fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>told of old, that <hi>Hereſies muſt be,</hi> &amp;c. The Apoſtle gives the reaſon, <hi>That the ſound and approved Truth, may be known from fond and received Hereſie.</hi> The ground and ſeminary of broaching them, may be, beſides the common and inbred corruption of Pride and Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, which mankinde is prone unto, that ſo many ſorts of men in many places do deſpiſe and ſpeak againſt the Scriptures, although the Rule of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Faith: Others unwarranted, do undertake to teach and expound the ſame. In diſordered and licentious times, cauſed through the diſtractions of a Civil War, it may fall out, as a <note n="*" place="margin">S. <hi>Jerome.</hi>
               </note> Father of the Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plained it did in his, of Scripture-Teachers, of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounders
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:116061:25"/>
of the Myſteries in Divinity, cited by a learned Divine upon the words of the Apoſtle, char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <hi>the unlearned and unſtable for wreſting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures to their own deſtruction;</hi> whoſe preſumption (the Divine tells us) is enough to produce any Schiſm or Hereſie. <q>
                  <hi>Sola,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Scripturarum ars eſt, quam ſibi omnes paſsim vendicant; hanc garrula annus, hanc delirus ſenex, hanc ſophtſta verboſus</hi> (he might have filled up the meaſure of his Complaint, by diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many other ſorts of unlearned People intruding into the holy Myſtery of Divinity) <hi>hanc univerſi praeſumunt, lacerant, docent antequam diſcunt.</hi> Every one preſuming upon his parts and gifts to be a Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher and Interpreter of Scripture, whereas Practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioners in other Arts can contain themſelves within the bounds of their own Profeſſion. The reaſon why the unlearned are ſo bold, may be their want of ability to diſcern the ſtrength of the Objections which may be made againſt them. By the unlearned, is not meant he who hath not read a multitude of Authors, but he who taking upon him to divide the Word of God, is raw and unexperienced, or if he hath experience, wants judgment to make uſe of it. The anguiſh that theſe raſh Preſumers bring unto the diſcreeter ſort of Brethren, cannot but be great, when being convinced of their unſound opinions, for the maintaining that which with much boldneſs and open falſhoods they have averred, they pretend the Authority of the Word, and whatſoever con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit is begotten in their heads, the Spirit of God to be preſently the Author of it: when as learned and judicious men, in whom the Lord hath put wiſdom and underſtanding, to know how to work all maner
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:116061:25"/>
of work for the ſervice of the Sanctuary, like <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zaleel</hi> and <hi>Aholiab,</hi> refuſe much of the ſtuff which is offered them. Scripture is given to all to learn: to teach, to interpret, only to a few. It is the voice of God confeſſed by all, that the ſenſe is Scripture, not the words; it cannot therefore be avoided but that he that wilfully ſtrives to faſten ſome ſenſe of his own, other then the nature of the place will bear, muſt needs take upon him the Perſon of God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, and to be an inditer of Scripture. <hi>No Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is of private Interpretation,</hi> There can be but two certain and infallible Interpreters of it, either it Self or the Holy Ghoſt the Author of it; it ſelf doth then expound it ſelf, when the words and circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances do ſound unto the Reader, the prime natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and principal ſenſe. Beſides theſe two, all other Interpretation is private; wherefore as the Lords of the Philiſtines ſometimes ſaid of the Kine which drew the Ark unto <hi>Bethſhemeſh; If they go of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, then is this from God,</hi> but <hi>if they go another way then it is not from God, it is but ſome chance that hath happened to us,</hi> So it may be ſaid of all pretended ſenſe of Scripture, If Scripture come unto it of it ſelf, then it is from God, but if it go another way, or violently urged or goaded on, then it is but a matter of chance, of man's deviſing and invention. As for thoſe marvellous diſcourſes of ſome, framed upon preſumption of the Spirit's help in private, in judging and interpreting difficult places in Scripture, their boldneſs cannot be ſufficiently wondered at. The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit is a thing of dark &amp; ſecret operation, the maner of it none can deſcry. As underminers are never ſeen till they have wrought their purpoſes, ſo the Spirit is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:116061:26"/>
never perceiv'd but by its effects. The effects of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, as far as they concern knowledg &amp; inſtruction, are not particular information for reſolution in any doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful caſe, for this were plainly Revelation, but as the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel</hi> w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> was ſent to <hi>Cornclius,</hi> informs him not, but ſends him to <hi>Peter</hi> to School; ſo the Spirit teaches not, but ſtirs up in us a deſire to learn, deſire to learn makes us thirſt after the means, pious ſedulity and carefulneſs makes us watchful in the choice, and diligent in the uſe of the means. The promiſe to the Apoſtles of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which <hi>ſhould lead them into all Truth,</hi> was made good unto them by private and ſecret inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their underſtandings with the knowledg of high and heavenly Myſteries, which as yet had never en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred into the conceit of any man; the ſame promiſe is made unto us, but fulfilled after another maner. For what was written by Revelation in their hearts, for our inſtruction have they written in their Books: to us for information, otherwiſe then out of theſe Books, the Spirit ſpeaketh not. When the Spirit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generates a man, it infuſeth no knowledg of any point of Faith, but ſends him to the Church, and to the Scriptures; when it ſtirs him up to newneſs of life, it exhibits not unto him an <hi>Inventory</hi> of his ſins, but either ſuppoſes them known in the Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, of which no man can be ignorant, or ſends him to learn from the mouth of his Teachers. More then this in the ordinary proceeding of the Spirit in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of inſtruction, no ſober man could ever yet de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine. So that to ſpeak of the help of the Spirit in private, either in dijudicating or interpreting of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, is to ſpeak they know not what. Which is the rather worth the notice, becauſe by experience we
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:116061:26"/>
have learnt how apt men are to call their own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits <hi>the Spirit,</hi> which becauſe it is an eſpeciall Error charged by a <note n="*" place="margin">S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtine.</hi>
                  </note> Father of the Church on this kinde of men, to be the more prone to kindle <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Contention</hi> in the Church, by how much the more they ſeem to themſelves to be endued with a more eminent meaſure of Spirit then their Brethren, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves reproof, whilſt under pretence of interpreting, they rudely and raſhly broach their own conceits.</q> Sir, there may be much ſpent upon this one effect of this <hi>Civil War,</hi> I have been too long in theſe digreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the labour of another man; but that you may be hereby ſatisfied how improbable it is that well-bred, wiſe, and learned men, however Malice hath caſt this Contumely on them, do wilfully and willingly coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance theſe unlearned Sectaries, and rude Intruders into <hi>Moſes</hi> Chair. They are willing for ought it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to the contrary, to promote the means of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, to give encouragement to the increaſe thereof, by their favour and reſpect ſhewn unto the Schools and Nurſeries, in their Acts and Ordinances exempting them from any Charge or Taxe for raiſing Monies to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards this War, by placing painfull and ſober Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours in the ſeverall Societies of the Univerſities, to reduce them to their former temper, of acquiring Learning and good Manners, that what the fury and fierceneſs of a War was likely to demoliſh and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy, is yet recoverable by the care and induſtry of their Governours, and whereas there is a diſproporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Antipathy between Science (a ſoft, milde and tender habit) and a War (a privative and deſtroying judgment) there is yet by God's bleſſing left a poſſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and means of a Regreſs from a War and Garriſon
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:116061:27"/>
of Souldiers in one of them, to an acquiſition of Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, and Nurſery of Scholars. Neither doth the Parliament, for ought we ſee, neglect or diſ-eſteem the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> or other <hi>Seminaries</hi> of Learning, or take away the Endowments of Colledges, as their Enemies give out, becauſe of able and learned Scholars of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> and elſwhere, ſequeſtred for a time, and diſpoſſeſt of part of their Eſtates, by reaſon of their conſtant prejudice and ill-will againſt the <hi>Parliament</hi> and their <hi>Proceedings,</hi> the Parliament knowing ſuch to be intereſted, engag'd, &amp; not long ſince ſeaſoned by the Enemy Garriſoning in one of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities,</hi> to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive their overthrow. Delinquents Compounding for their offence, or the Sequeſtring their eſtates (a Puniſhment inflicted by the Parliament) is eaſier to be born, taking withall the juſtice of the Cauſe, which is here examined, then the Confiſcating the Parliaments Friends eſtates for adhering to that ſide; which they could not but expect, when Spectators only taking part on neither ſide, are in danger, and a Law enforced for their <note n="a" place="margin">See the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, p. 27.</note> 
               <hi>forbearing to defend the King.</hi> The unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of this Diſeaſe <hi>(viz.)</hi> of Hereſies abounding, of the unlearned their broaching them, of the cauſes and conſequences thereof, is to be aſcribed to the Authors and Occaſion of the War; before which, and <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Jewell</hi> in his Apole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie of the Church of England.</note> many years together, the Church was at Peace and Unity within it ſelf, it had none of this ſort of Adverſaries to diſturb the ſame. But enough of this. To your other Objection, <hi>That Independency</hi> (as 'tis called) <hi>denies all Order and Government,</hi> when as they have Remonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and Proteſted for the contrary: Whatſoever they may for a time, for reaſons beſt known to themſelves, and upon the altering the preſent ſtate of things, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:116061:27"/>
and Act to the laying aſide Degrees and Orders heretofore in uſe, They or their ſucceſſors may when the ſtorm threatned is over, the danger of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing overcome is paſt, reduce and bring the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this Nation, the courſe of Parliaments and other Conſtitutions into ſome part of their priſtine and former ſtate again. Rather the Royaliſt and Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terian ſeemes to give way to many practices tending to Irreligion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when as their ill-will and envy are ſo eager againſt the oppoſite Party (called <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents)</hi> that they will rather ſubmit unto, and joyn with the Turk or Jew, then to be maſtered by that Party betwixt whom and one of them there is a kinde of difference, no true or real, only a notional and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary one. The King's Parties Envy grows out of being overcome, and doth appear from the judgment and cenſure he hath of them, in the puniſhment had he prevailed he would have condemned them to. For of the moderate ſort of the Parliament and their Friends he holds them <note n="*" place="margin">See the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarat. of the Lords and Commons aſſembled at <hi>Oxford,</hi> &amp;c. printed there 1643 <hi>Pag.</hi> 24, 26, 27.</note> 
               <hi>unskilful, vulgar ſpirited, weak and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced men for ſiding with the People,</hi> as they terme it, <hi>and their multitudes,</hi> the eminent and more active ſort <hi>Traytors, Perjured All,</hi> yea <hi>the Neutrals too, for not offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to defend the King,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>according to the Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance</hi> (The Parliament Party having a more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derate and milde judgment of the King's, knowing many of them reſtleſs and virulent as yet, judging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers <hi>Miſtaken</hi> only, ſome of them being led away through Ambition and aſpiring thoughts to adhere to the King upon the Proverb of <hi>No fiſhing to the Sea, nor ſervice to the Court,</hi> whereupon the Parliament have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly paſſed by the errors &amp; tranſgreſſions of the King's, by an eaſy Mulcting them, ſo that if the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:116061:28"/>
at the firſt had been no worſe nor no more erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neouſly paſſed againſt the one then it was againſt the other Party, the War had ſoon been ended &amp; a Peace reſtored) By the King's Party's large extenſion of which Oath, they may bring many within the compaſs of Perjury. The King being to maintain the Laws, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and bound as a Supream Power <hi>to take vengeance on evil doers, without which He bears the ſword in vain,</hi> as the Subjects are to their Allegiance; the Obligation is reciprocal, as the two Houſes of Parliament, when allowed to be, &amp; ſtiled by King Himſelf a Parliament, with an unanimous conſent obſerved in their <note n="*" place="margin">See the Meſſage printed with the above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, dat. <hi>March.</hi> 9 1643.</note> meſſage ſent unto Him in a few words expreſſed; If the King may diſpenſe with His Oath, and that <hi>He reckons Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf accomptable to none but God,</hi> which the Parliament objects as a Maxime &amp; Ground for any Tyranny, the Enacting Laws is of no value as to the King, and how far ſwearing Allegiance is to the Subject, is the queſtion. In this only lies the odds, upon the event of which Party ſhall prevaile in this War, If the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall, They are notwithſtanding ſubject to the Reproach and Obloquy of ſlanderous tongues and pens, Their Demeanor not free from beeing cenſured, Reviled and Charged with ſeveral Crimes as their Accuſers pleaſe, No ſuch ſalve for them as for the King, in caſe He ſhould have prevailed by what means ſoever, no man ſhould have dared to have queſtioned His proceedings, or the means by which He prevailed, in caſe He had Conquered. The wiſe man asks, <hi>who ſhall ſay that a King is</hi> falſe <hi>or wicked?</hi> and the <hi>French</hi> Proverb tells us <hi>Que la Coronne unifois prinſe oſte toute ſorte de defaults,</hi> The meaning is, when the King ſhall have regained His former ful and Regall Power, the Parliament and theirs then born down, His re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſeſſing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:116061:28"/>
His Crown ſhall as well quit all quarels and exceptions and cancel all diſputes, as it ſhall clear all manner of faults and Crimes concerning the means how He attained His Conqueſt. The ſuſtance of that Oath, even now objected, is in theſe words, <hi>That the Pope hath no Power either of himſelf or by any means to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe the King, nor Authorize any Forraign Prince to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vade or annoy Him, to bear Arms againſt or offer Him violence or hurt. That no Declaration, Sentence of Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unication or Deprivation made by the Pope, hath Power to abſolve any Subject from his Allegiance, by reaſon or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of any ſuch Sentence or Declaration, &amp;c.</hi> The reaſon of enjoyning the Oath of Supremacy, is expreſſed in the Preamble of that <note n="*" place="margin">See the Statut. 1<hi rend="sup">mo.</hi> 
                  <hi>Eliz.</hi> 1. and the Preamble thereof.</note> Statute made for taking the ſame, which was therefore done in oppoſition to Forraign Princes, Prelates, States and Potentates, by reaſon of great exacted ſums which they by their u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurping took from the Subjects of this Kingdom<hi>:</hi> ſo that the Oath of Supremacy concerns the <hi>Subject's duty towards the King His Heirs and Succeſſors in their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſing to grant or pay any Tribute of Power to Forraigners, but to oppoſe and reſiſt all ſuch; to acknowledg the antient Jurisdictions, Superorities and Preheminencies due to the King or His Succeſſors, againſt and in oppoſition to ſuch uſurpings.</hi> The words and prime ſenſe of the ſwearer beeing <hi>That he will renounce and forſake all Forraign Jurisdictions, Superiorities and Authorities,</hi> thence <hi>That he will defend the King His Heirs and Succeſſor's Juris<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, Authority,</hi> &amp;c. So the Competition for Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemmency, Power, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is betwixt the King His Heirs &amp; Succeſſors on the one, and Forreigners only on the other part, and by reaſon of ſuch exactions practiſed by ſuch Forraigners. The Royaliſts to make good
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:116061:29"/>
this charge of ſuppoſed Perjury in breaking the Oath of Supremacy and Allegiance, which they cannot, unleſs they gain a Power, leave no ways untried, no ſtone unmoved, what Wit and Invention can bring in to promote their Induſtry. By all the Artificiall and feigned means they can to keep up their Party, as by ſowing the Tares of Diſcord and Sedition amongſt the Parliament party and their friends, hoping at laſt to reap themſelves the fruit and harveſt, cunningly and inſenſibly carrying it on, under fair pretences to the Peace and Publique good, by their Pamphleters kept, it may be thought in pay and penſion, to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie and talk high of their Cauſe and their good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes, to vilifie and depreſs the Parliament's &amp; Theirs, to publiſh and divulge their Falſhoods, in hope to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage them and their Friends, and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the unſtable and unreſolved, (as many men unto whom the Juſtice of this Quarrell having ſeemed doubtfull, have ſhewn themſelves) would fall in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſtronger ſide; By reporting of their own ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord without warrant from the King, more indulgent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and favourably on His behalf, then any of his own actions have declared, which inſinuatings and report<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings in favour unto Him, have peradventure powerfully wrought on the unſtable, wavering in their affections; By their ſubtile practices to purſue and continue their Deſigns, diſguiſing them under ſeveral habits, that <hi>what a Lions ſtrength cannot, the Foxes skin put on may work,</hi> each one acting his ſeverall part to the beſt ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage and improvement of the whole; ſome bemoan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their dejected and low condition (thereby to draw pity to their ſuggeſted wrongfull ſufferings) not that they think it ſo, but that they may be thereby the leſs
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:116061:29"/>
perceived to exerciſe their Art of gaining their ſtrength and Power again, both by nouriſhing Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contents and Seditions here at home, and having Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors and Emiſſaries to ſolicite their Cauſe abroad: By traducing and depreſsing the eſteem of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and their Actions, to render their Perſons the more odious and contemptible, thence the more weak and eaſie to be ſubdued. By contriving and inventing Falſhoods, ſometimes in the nature of reporting Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies in favour to the King and His ſucceſs, as to give out <hi>how happy and victorious He or His Poſterity ſhall be.</hi> Many the like deviſed Inventions in the nature of Predictions and Divinings, ſome whereof made on purpoſe, others as vainly reported and given out, to give hopes unto His Party to try if the reporting ſuch Prophecyings can bring the fruits of their endeavours within the compaſs of ſuch Propheſies fulfilled. By ſeditious Pamphletings and privily diſperſing ſuch, by publiſhing other more weighty, no leſs ſeditious Books, obtruding them on ſuch Authors as they pleaſe, all to affect the Reader: ſometimes in the King<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>s name, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in His behalf, particularly that Poſthume one called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, by many men given out to be His, which if the Parliaments often Declarations, Charges and Remonſtrances againſt Him and His Proceedings be true, thoſe applauded Tracts and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditations in that Book, are but a reinforced diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling put upon Him, and the Greek words might be rather tranſlated into the <hi>Image and Pourtraicture of a Counterfeit</hi> (For the Author counterfeiting the King, makes the Falſhoods and Impoſtures obtruded upon the King to be his own) <hi>then into the Image of a Prince.</hi> Whoſoever ſhall read the Parliaments often Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:116061:30"/>
and Charges againſt the King, ſet forth ſince the beginning of this War, not denyed or anſwered by any of His Party, ſaving in a recriminatory and ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing way, calling the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and their Adherents, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels:</hi> Or who ſhall read the <note n="a" place="margin">Written by Mr. <hi>Tho. May</hi> 1647. begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning at <hi>Pag</hi> 6. unto <hi>pag.</hi> 46. Moreover how Corruption and Oppreſſions irremediably grew through the Diſcontinuance and defect of Parliaments not called, through the often Diſſolving them in the time of His Reign and His Declarations publiſhed againſt the Members of ſome of them; which the Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian reports, <hi>the dejected People were forced to read with patience, and to allow againſt their own Reaſon.</hi> Wherein many things are there obſerved, concerning the maner of the Scots proceedings before and even at the firſt beginnings of theſe Troubles, Their ſufferings, how by their humble applying themſelves unto the King for redreſs, they could have none. In fine, the averſneſs of the Engliſh People from a War with <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> pag. 46.</note> Hiſtory of the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> ſummarily reciting the Kings averſneſs from Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments, cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg that <note n="b" place="margin">See the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> on that Tract.</note> Book, whatſoever the fair and plauſible flouri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes in it pretend <hi>of the King's inclining to and deſiring Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> to be falſly and injuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly Charged on him<hi>:</hi> Falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, becauſe They cannot but know how unwillingly and ſeldom He called any, how oft he did diſſolve or attempt to diſſolve them when they were called; whence the Anſwer meets the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, <hi>That the Parliament's Party did begin the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations for a War before the King's.</hi> The King's <note n="c" place="margin">Mr. <hi>May</hi> his Hiſtory.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſs to call Parliaments, His <note n="d" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Hollis</hi> his Speech.</note> awing and diſſolving them at pleaſure often and long before any preparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons could be thought of for a War, may ſatisfie the objection: when as moreover, divers of his Friends and Party have long before fortified and furniſhed their houſes in many parts of the Kingdom with Arms and Ammunition, no other notice taken till of late then of adorning ſuch for ſtrength and ſplendor, which w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> ſome ſmal addition became ſtrong Gariſons for him. The Parliaments friends had none or not ſo
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:116061:30"/>
many Holds ſo ſoon or ſuddenly to be fortified for their defence. The Author to have made his own Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtures and Diſſembling the King's deſires of Peace and Juſtice, the more compleat and full, might with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out bluſhing aſwell have added one Treatiſe more to the twenty eight, to have rendered the King free and innocent from that great offence of the Maſſacres committed in the Iriſh Troubles, and declared Him guiltleſs of ſo much of his Subjects Blood as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion there hath coſt. A Treatiſe added to that Book with ſuch an Apology on the King's behalf, might have paſſed under the ſame belief and credit as other well penned paſſages in the Book, when as the contrary is well known, as the two Houſes of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have in their Charges and Remonſtrances ſet forth to the publike view, ſuch Tranſactions of the King's betwixt Him and the Iriſh concerning His con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niving at and favoring the Rebels there, under colour of raiſing freinds and Aſſiſtance thence, to ſerve Him in the War againſt the Parliament here, as to finde Him guilty of the Blood ſpilt in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom as in This. Injuriouſly charged on the King, in that the Author and Reader alſo, if a Friend to Him and would have the Book to be reputed His, do wound His honor and render the maner of His death the more unchriſtian then otherwiſe it would be judged, when whileſt the Life is mortal they make the vices of Diſſembling and uncharitableneſs to be ſurviving and immortall motions. The reporting it to be the King's, ſeems beſides, to blemiſh the credit of thoſe Penitentiall Expreſſions therein, derogating from the ſerious, retired, and ſolid parts wherewith He was endowed; then doubtleſs free from the affectated
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:116061:31"/>
words, whereof the Book is full, in defence of the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold actions of His incident to this War. Many of them too weakly excuſed, to be His, although in an handſome way of writing (to poſſeſs the belief of men) obtruded on Him by indeed the Author of the Book: Namely, and more particularly, That weakly objected Crime of the Author, in the King's name, blaming <hi>the Parliaments Army for diſcovering the King's Letters taken at</hi> Naſeby <hi>Fight, upbraiding them with an uncivil and inhumane dealing in publiſhing them.</hi> Who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever ſhall praiſe the Book, and thence draw ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe unto the King, ſhould for the better glory of it have expunged ſome improbable and extravagant paſſages, and inſerted others more neceſſary and ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory, one Tract at leaſt of the King's care and zeal for the ſecurity and maintenance of the true Proteſtant Religion; what He hath written or acted to clear thoſe doubts, to wipe away thoſe Jealouſies had of Him, no where to be found in the Book, and a great Incentive to this Contention. Some paſſages there are, plauſibly ſet down by way of cenſuring and ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt Novelties and new faſhions in Religion, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Form and Maner how God is to be ſerved and prayed unto, againſt the extemporary and unpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meditated Prayers of ſome Miniſters, and the like, ſomewhat alſo by way of <note n="*" place="margin">In the Treatiſe concerning the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer.</note> defending the Common-Prayer-Book, about which there is no laſting and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall diſcord betwixt the King's Party, and the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: For, for ought we know, it may with ſome al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terations to be made, be hereafter received again, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then the Peace or Diſcipline of the Church ſhall be diſturbed about the Form and Method of the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgie, the Common-Prayer-Book if in ſome parts al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:116061:31"/>
little differing from the Directory, ſaving in the exerciſe of the Miniſters abilities, and their choice of words and quantities, how much, or how little <hi>their Prayers and Divine Service</hi> ſhall be. Nothing in that Book delivered touching the Subſtance of Religion, whether we take it in point of Maners, or in Faith, or Doctrine, or of His profeſſing to defend and ſecure it from Superſtition and Idolatry, as part of His <note n="*" place="margin">Deſenſor Fidei.</note> Title implies, Rather the contrary as to the matter of ſuſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, by reaſon of His profeſt indulgence to the Queen, as the Author preſents Him, <hi>Bewatling Her abſence, and Her Fortunes, &amp;c.</hi> And whatſoever His advertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the King's name are to the Prince, in a skil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Dialect expreſſed to perſwade him <hi>to begin and end with God,</hi> with other good Inſtructions frequently gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven him, <hi>to be well grounded in his Religion, to keep the middle way between the Pomp of ſuperſtitious Tyranny, and the meaneſs of Phantaſt que Anarchy.</hi> The Councell delivered is good, if the ſeaſon of the delivery (a weighty circumſtance) be obſerved as well, That the ſuſpition and fear of the growth of ſuperſtitious Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny in the peacefull times, were no greater then that of Anarchy, eaſie to be let in through the licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and confuſedneſs of a Civil War. And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is that Councell given? As if the Parliament did intend, or had brought in Anarchy, or deviſed to root out all Government. No Calumny whereby to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Them and their proceedings odious and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is of extent enough to ſerve and ſatiate their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies appetite. The Parliament in their Prudence and Experience might diſcern a reaſon for the changing the Monarchicall into ſome other Form, of as much conducement to the maintenance of Peace and Juſtice.
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:116061:32"/>
But what that Religion is which the Author enjoyns the Prince unto, whether oppoſite to Popery or <note n="*" place="margin">The ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuall ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſing Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours and Schiſmes is charged on him. <hi>p.</hi> 138.</note> Schiſm (This like Weeds in Corn, choaking and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering it's growth, That like Mildews, blaſting and deſtroying it) he defining not, makes it ſeem doubtfull to the Reader. For preſently after, he would have <hi>the Prince his judgment and reaſon to ſeal to that ſacred bond which education hath written in him, in which he hath been bred.</hi> Let a computation be had of his yong years, how in his infancy uncapable of diſcerning the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences of Religion before this War began, where and with whom he hath lived theſe ſeven or eight years ſince it began, all men will not believe that to be the Reformed Proteſtant Religion which is there enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him (take it in its purity, or as the corruption of times hath faſhioned it) the Prince ſeems to go in a contrary Diameter to either, as to thoſe inſtructions given him by the Author, by what is reported of his favouring and entertaining at his Court the greateſt and moſt known Catholiques, Forraigners of all parts, ſetting aſide his Proteſtant and native Engliſh. So that either he takes not thoſe Inſtructions to be truly and genuinely the King's, or little obſerves them. That which ſhould have been expunged out of the Book to make it the more admired His, is that one paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage (ſtrange amongſt the reſt) about <hi>His challenging the Parliament for diſcovering the Letters taken at</hi> Naſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by <hi>Fight,</hi> even how mentioned. For, who ſhall look upon a War where Parties are reſolutely engaged to defend their own, to conſume their Enemies Forces, as His Party did by Fire and Sword, laying waſte many Villages and Towns, not ſparing their own Friends, ſo they might be avenged on their Enemies, will not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:116061:32"/>
that in the heat of War any regard ſhould be had to the concealing or divulging Letters; when the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition was ſo extream, the enmity ſo violent, that no other cenſure ſerves to fill up His Parties malice, then to judg the Parliament and their Friends <hi>Falſe and Rebels:</hi> From which calumny and ſtain faſtened on their Credit and Poſterity, They will rather fight it out to vindicate themſelves and their Friends from <hi>Attainders, Forfeitures</hi> threatned <note n="a" place="margin">In the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration printed at <hi>Oxford</hi> 1643 <hi>pag.</hi> 27.</note> on Them, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice their Lives to the juſtice of their Cauſe, then un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the guilt of thoſe aſperſions; the diſpute reſting ſtill upon the Queſtion <hi>Who be Rebels?</hi> To reſiſt and oppoſe the Will of a Lawfull King, may more reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble the name of Rebell, and in that acception the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament and their Friends may by the King and His be reputed Rebels. Thoſe who by practice or councell ſhall infringe or ſubvert the Laws and Liberties of a free-born People, although in a ſmall degree of exacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and oppreſſion (the Laws have their Metes and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits, to bound out unto every man his own) are in the judgment of a Religious and Learned <note n="b" place="margin">K. <hi>James</hi>'s Speech be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, <hi>pag.</hi> 14.</note> Prince, no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then <hi>Vipers, Peſts,</hi> and <hi>Traytors</hi> to a Kingdom; ſtyled in theſe latter times <hi>evill Counſellours</hi> to the King.</p>
            <p>The <hi>violating the ancient Law of</hi> Magna Charta, <hi>ſo induſtriouſly and religiouſly preſerved by our Anceſtours, and above thirty ſeverall times confirmed in Parliament</hi> (to uſe the very words of the Lords and Commons aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembled at <hi>Oxford,</hi> in their Declarations printed there) is objected againſt the Parliament ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> to be <hi>a</hi> 
               <note n="c" place="margin">See the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, <hi>p.</hi> 19.</note> 
               <hi>bold &amp; avowed tranſgreſsion of the Laws and Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties of the People,</hi> as if the Party of thoſe Lords and Commons were altogether free from the like tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions; ſo they may in like manner object the vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:116061:33"/>
the late King's Grant to <hi>the Petition of Right,</hi> when they and their Party are as culpable as the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments Party are. The pillaging the Earl of <hi>Stam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford's</hi> houſe in Leiceſter ſhire by the Kings Party commanding there, an undoubted and notorious Felo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny by the Letter of the Law, all His Souldiers guilty of the ſame. The ſtorming by day and night, and breaking into the Marqueſſe of <hi>Wincheſter's</hi> Houſe in in Hant-ſhire by the Parliaments Party, the higheſt degree of Burglary. Many the like Hoſtile actions may be inſtanced in on either ſide, but how? In the heat of War, in the purſuit of Conqueſt, each Party ſtriving which ſhould overcome and deſtroy their Enemy.</p>
            <p>One other paſſage of that Book as unjuſtly and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probably delivered <hi>(viz.)</hi> The excuſe and plauſible reaſons given of <hi>the King's going to the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, attended with ſo many armed Gentlemen,</hi> as the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the Treatiſe concerning the King's going to the Houſe of Commons to ſurprize the five Members.</note> Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor ſayes, <hi>was no unwonted thing for the Majeſty of a King to be ſo attended, eſpecially in diſcontented times.</hi> The times were not then ſo diſcontented as that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heard of and horrid act did afterwards make them, and might have made them at that time, had but the hand of one deſperate Caitiffe given fire to his Piſtols ready cockt, the Houſe of Commons being near full, and equall in number to the Forces prepared againſt them, no man knows how diſaſtrous and fatall the event had been: neither could the King juſtly fear <hi>to be aſſaulted or affronted by any in the Houſe,</hi> as the Author intimates, None in the Houſe within, being armed an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that the King's Guard without. The Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor thinks that he hath handſomly palliated that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, under colour of the King's ſtanding in need of a
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:116061:33"/>
Guard, rendring <hi>thoſe His Attendants there ſhort of His ordinary Guard:</hi> but whether he means ſhort in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, or in forcible array, he declares not. Many other paſſages as improbable as theſe, are the diſcourſes of the Book, too tedious to recite, the examining and ſearch whereof is beſides my purpoſe. It ſeems to have little of it of the King, it hath Elegancy of wit enough, and affectation of expreſſions to be applauded, inconſiſtent with a ſound and Chriſtian wiſdom whereunto His preſent Condition was to be fitted: and Charity en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes not to think it His, when full of ſo many un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charitable expreſſions although clothed in pious eja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culations. The Author is too blame to father upon Him ſuch intermixtures of Scorn and Piety, in ſome parts of it Devotion and Penitencie, in other Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurings and Detractings, compiled probably by ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Authors, the off-ſpring too unlike it ſelf to be truly and unviocally begot by one and the ſelf-ſame Parent. The words of Scorn are, where the Author ſpeaking of the King's impeaching ſix Members of both Houſes of High Treaſon, terms them in a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainful way [<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, pag. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Half a dozen]</hi> which number is all one as ſix, but the manner of the ſlighting Phraſe <hi>[Half a dozen]</hi> unbecoming the grave and ſerious Majeſty of a King, eſpecially He being in ſorrow and affliction as the Author preſents Him, Not to be applyed to Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen of quality, rather to things of cheap and mean accompt vendible in Tradeſmens Shops. The whole Book, indeed, if throughly ſcanned, is but a fine-dreſſed Invective againſt the one, an Apology for the other Party, fitly penned to keep up the affections of His friends, to win and move compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion even from His enemies: for whileſt the Author
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:116061:34"/>
preſents him innocent and injured, compaſſion begets affections towards the Perſon injured, throws diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace and calumny on the Perſons injuring. The beſt, moſt acceptable and likelyeſt to be believed Tract had been, if the Author in His Book had obſerved and declared, that the King peradventure in the time of His greateſt troubles, and when the Victory ſtood doubtful, did intend, as He did then profeſs in many excellent and winning ſpeeches delivered at <hi>York, Shrewsbury, Nottingham</hi> and elſe where, <hi>to preſerve the Laws and Liberties of His People, to maintain the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion, the Power and Priviledg of Parliament,</hi> which He could not but foreſee (take it either in the upright heart of a pious Prince intending it) that His real and ſincere intentions to maintain the ſame were His beſt breſt plate and ſafeſt guard, or (take it in the politick part of a cunning Enemy meaning nothing leſs) That ſuch Profeſſions were His next way to Conquer by; but when He had thereby conquered what ſafety or ſecurity was there to be expected, that He ſhould not return unto and be governed by the advice of thoſe evil Counſellors who had at the firſt drawn Him away, and by degrees might have wrought upon His affections to the curbing, if not to the ſuppreſſing thoſe Laws and Liberties, to the puniſhing thoſe whom He had adjudged and called Travtors, Rebels?</p>
            <p>The High Treaſon charged on the Parliament by the Author in the Perſon of the King, ſoftly and mildely inſtilled into the Readers ears in that Book, down-rightly and roughly by the divided Members ſitting at <hi>Oxford</hi> in their Declaration printed there; muſt be underſtood either <hi>le Crime de Majeſtie</hi> or <hi>le</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:116061:34"/>
               <hi>Crime de Fauſonnerie,</hi> The Crime againſt His Majeſty, is either againſt His Perſon or His Honor: againſt His Perſon, as to conſpire or intend His death, or to lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vie War againſt Him: againſt His Honour, as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flour the Queen His wife, His daughter, or the wife of His Heir, to kill thoſe His principal Officers of State, ſpecified within the <hi>Statute of</hi> 25. Edw. 3. <hi>compriſing all Crimes adjudged Treaſon.</hi> Flattery and a temporary conformity to the preſent and Arbitrary will of a Prince, are but ſhadows only, the true ſubſtance and higheſt degree of honouring Him is, when men in Place and Authority deputed thereunto, ſhall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour (as the Parliament Proteſted and were credibly believed) to have puniſhed all Indignities, Affronts and Crimes which had or might have been committed againſt the Peace, His Crown and Dignity. The other ſort of High Treaſon is <hi>Le Crime de Fauſonnerie,</hi> two ways committed, either by counterfeiting the Coyne or the Great Seal. Now with which ſort of High Treaſon doth the King's Party charge the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments? either with the firſt a purpoſe to deſtroy His Perſon, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as above recited? or the latter, the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting the Great Seal? not againſt His Perſon, The obſerving this Diſcourſe throughout ſetting forth the Maner and Original of the Contention betwixt the King and His People (the Parliament only is as it were the Judg between both) doth manifeſt how impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable and untrue it doth appear, that the Parliament when five or ſix years ſince accuſed of Treaſon by the divided Members ſitting at <hi>Oxford,</hi> did, then or at any time before, intend to levy and offenſive War, to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine or conſpire the Kings Death. It is one thing ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally to intend, out of malice prepenſed and fore-thought
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:116061:35"/>
to deviſe or contrive a purpoſe, another thing through an inevitable neceſſity to act a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt and contrary to the intention of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors. If, by the way, any exquiſite or choice <note place="margin">☞</note> Wits, of a more ſublimate reach then their Fellow-Subjects, did know or could have diſcovered any dark or ſecret contrivances of ſuch intendment or conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy againſt His Perſon, deeming all others <hi>of a narrow and lower capacity, ignorant and dull-ſpirited,</hi> they were too blame to conceal the Plot, the manner and means of effecting it: They had Power, Confidence and Liberty enough, when the divided Members being of their Party ſate at <hi>Oxford,</hi> and there accuſed the Parliament ſitting at <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> of many treaſonable Deſigns preſent, which (the quality of the Perſons accuſing being conſidered) they would leave no means unattempted to enhaunce their Power, to make good their Charge, for the Juſtice ſake of their Proceedings. So then the Caſe is briefly thus, The King's Party (together with the divided Members ſitting at <hi>Oxford)</hi> have in their Declarations Printed there, charged the Parliament of High Treaſon, which Party to make good their Charge have ſtriven and done their utmoſt to enforce their own to conſume the Parliaments ſtrength, as by inviting Forreigners and Natives to come in to their aſſiſtance, yea <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See the Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration <hi>pag.</hi> 26. &amp; 27.</note> Neutrals too, under pain of forfeiting their Allegiance and breach of Oath. The Parliament have on the other ſide, to defend themſelves and friends from ſuch guilt, the Neutrals alſo from the cenſure of <hi>Allegiance-forfeiting,</hi> as much contended to abate and take away the King's Parties Strength.</p>
            <p>Whereas the Objection now is, <hi>That the Parliament</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:116061:35"/>
               <hi>having of late, and many years together, conſiſted of three Eſtates, King, Lords and Commons, ceaſes now to be a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament;</hi> 'Tis anſwered, 'tis no leſs a Parliament by His death, then by His voluntary and continuated ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence in perſon and affections; Beſides, to ſatisfie the Objectors arguing, That <hi>by want of a King there is no ſuch Court or Government, as that the want of Him doth totally vacate both.</hi> There be other ſorts of Government known to all thoſe that have read the Politiques. Howbeit the Parliament hath heretofore conſiſted of three Eſtates (one of which is divided into two, Lords Spiritual and Temporal) Parliaments have been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore held, the <note n="*" place="margin">In the time of <hi>Edw.</hi> 1 at St <hi>Edmonds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury, Clero excluſo.</hi> Crompt. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdict. fol. 19.</note> one excluded. If by reaſon of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venience in ſucceeding times they have diſcovered cauſe for the aboliſhing any of the other, preſerving the Power and Government unto themſelves, and therefore have changed the Monarchical into ſome other Form, They have not done it meerly as Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors, to give new Laws unto the Conquered, but as a juſt Power lawfully convened, to defend and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the old from being broken and trampled on. In their diſpoſing and conſtituting a Government, there are two things to be conſidered, the fact of Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, the equity and reaſon of the fact; as to the one, None will deny but it is within the compaſs of a Conquering Power to alter, abrogate, repeal and conſtitute: as to the reaſon and equity of ſo doing, that is to be left to the judgment and experience of thoſe who do it. If the Court of Parliament have or ſhall require obedience to their Power, they require no more then what the Apoſtle enjoyns; <hi>Let every ſoul be ſubject to the higher Powers, for there is no Power but of God, the Powers</hi> that be <hi>are ordained of Him.</hi> And whereas They have Enacted and Declared That <hi>all</hi>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:116061:36"/>
               <hi>men in offices of Truſt and Qualified ſhall promiſe to be true and faithful to this Common Wealth</hi> wherein they live and from whence they hold and enjoy their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare, enforcing afterwards <hi>a Subſcription and Engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of Fealty <hi>unto the Common-Wealth, as tis now eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed without King or Houſe of Lords,</hi> the Peoples Subſcription thereunto is no more, if ſmall matters may hold reſemblance with greater, then Tenants of a Mannor unto a Lord thereof, unto whom, without diſputing the right or title, they promiſe their preſent Fealty. If the Lord unto whom they have heretofore done homage, be diſſeiſed by a ſtronger then himſelf, take it either of Right or Power, the Tenants are to pay their homage to the Lord <hi>that is,</hi> or by denying it become ſubject to be diſtrained to what they are worth: for it is not to the Power already paſt or that which is to come, but to the Powers <hi>that be,</hi> unto which Subjection is to be rendered. The Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies may be many, diſcovered by their Prudence, which Common-Wealths in a Monarchy may be ſubject to, when Princes in their abſolute and mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archicall eſtate abuſing their Power and Liberty, have become Tyrants over the Lives and Liberties of the People, aſſuming moreover ſo much unto themſelves or having been flattered by their Creatures to believe, <hi>That they are Gods on earth,</hi> as ſome of the Roman Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors did arrogate unto themſelves, That their Power is ſo vaſt, ſo ſoveraign, that the People were ordain'd for their behoof, to do and pay obedience in whatſoever they ſhall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mand, not the King for the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Quanquam Principes &amp; Subditi ſunt ex nume<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>tamen naturâ &amp; temports ratione prius fuerunt inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti Subditi. Principes ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro (niſi qui Tyrannidem uſurpâ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>) non naturá ut Patres, ſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uff<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>agio Subditorum &amp; conſenſu, certis conditionibus, Subditorum g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>atiâ conſtituti ſunt. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>de illud Domini apud</hi> Daniel 4 32. Scias quod domineiur Altiſſimus in regno hominum &amp; cu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> voluerit dabit illud. <hi>Ex quo ſequetur non Regum cauſâ Subdetos naſci, ſed R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ges commod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s Subd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>torum inſervire debere.</hi> Pucan Inſtitut. Theolog. tractat. de Magiſtrat. Thomas 1 part. 1 ſumma Theolog. quaeſt. 9. Art. 3. &amp; 4.</note> Peoples good,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:116061:36"/>
               <hi>That Kings were accomptable to none but God for</hi> whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they do, as of late 'twas threatned. The caſe is now quite otherwiſe then in former times: Hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have been Civil Wars, None like this, conſider it either in the manner for the beginning and continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of it, for the oppoſite and croſs Engagements even between the neereſt friends, between Equals in all Degrees Relations and Faculties, where the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaging at the firſt might be upon a Miſunderſtanding only, the proſecution reſts upon contending about ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral objects, rooted now in a Contention on the one ſide for, on the other ſide againſt abſolute Monarchy; both Parties pretending to one and the ſelf-ſame End, <hi>PEACE.</hi> The difference is as a long time it hath been, about the means how Peace hath been forfeited, how loſt; now how to regain and ſecure it when regained. The King's Party ſay (the moderate ſort out of an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willingneſs only to be Conquered, others of a fiercer ſpirit to be avenged on their adverſaries) the ſureſt and next way to Peace, is in the Prince his enjoying what his Father had; the Parliament judg quite contrary, for their own Safety, their Friends, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths. For whileſt the Prince ſeems to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply a threatning to be avenged on them which have been Actors in His Father's Death, as in his <note n="a" place="margin">See them recited in the Diurnal, from the 15. of <hi>February,</hi> the 21, 1649.</note> Letters to the Marqueſſe of <hi>Montroſſe,</hi> and to the Committee of Eſtates in <hi>Scotland</hi> (amongſt other things) he men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions who thoſe Actors be, his meaning may admit a large extent, to bring within his Cenſure all who have Adhered to, Fought or Acted for the Parliament, <note n="b" place="margin">See the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, What the late King's Parties Opinion is of the Covenant, and wherefore at the firſt contrived<hi>:</hi> In the Marginall Note in the 41. Page of this Book,</note> Covenanters, Non-Covenanters, with the
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:116061:37"/>
               <note n="a" place="margin">See the King's Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties Cenſure of them, in the Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion printed at <hi>Oxford,</hi> 1643.</note> Neutrals too, <hi>for not offering to defend the King.</hi> Not to defend or Forbear to Aſſiſt, is all one as to Offend. Whoſoever ſhall look on in a Conflict betwixt two oppoſite Parties, his Affections queſtionleſs incline (whatſoever his Actions are) more to one Party then to the other: So Neutrals, ſuch as have not acted for the King, being already by His Party adjudged <hi>Guilty,</hi> are ſubject to the Cenſure, and may be brought in within the compaſs of the Prince his meaning. On which account, whoſoever have not declared them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to have been ſome way for the King, will hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly avoid His Parties ſuſpition of having been for the other ſide, the Parliament. Now, where two Parties are extreamly oppoſite in their Endeavourings, the one to maintain what They have got, the other to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover what they have loſt, the judgment and practiſes on either part moving in a ſtrong oppoſition each to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, whether the Prevailing Power need to enjoyn or not new Tyes and Leagues to conform All to the Obedience of their Power and Government? In a doubtfull Conflict, where it is not agreed which Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty will prevail (for it is which we may believe, either the Diurnals publiſhed by, and on the Parliaments be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, or the Pamphletters on the King's, venting much of their Succeſs, and hopes to recover what they have loſt) it is requiſite in either caſe that the vanquiſhed and weaker Party ſhould joyn and unite themſelves by Engagements and Leagues to ſtrengthen and keep up the Power they have, when a ſmall matter of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding (as whether they ſhall Engage or not) turns the Scale in weighing what is to be done. The cunning and wit practiſed by many, Diſſwading from a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription to ſuch Engagement, the maner of their
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:116061:37"/>
practiſing of an abſtruſe and dark operation hardly to be perceived but by it's effects, <hi>the maintenance of ſedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> thence a purſuit of the hopes of Conquering by keeping up Diviſions, even in matters of ſmall weight or Difficulty.</p>
            <p>Sir, the ſcruple which ſome make, diſputing the quality, the reaſon of the Engagement which the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament hath enjoyned, is <hi>[That it is ſtrange and new which the People are to ſubſcribe unto.]</hi> A <note n="*" place="margin">St. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine.</hi>
               </note> Father of the Church ſhews what is to be expected in an Innovation in a Common-wealth, <hi>Ipſa mutatio quae utilitate adju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat, etiam novitate perturbat.</hi> The novity and the not examining the neceſsity of their enjoyning ſuch En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to bring all men into one and the ſame en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire judgment and agreement, the Enemy (divided now into ſeveral parties) his aym to keep men from accord and unity <hi>under pretence of the Conſcience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnared, inthralled by ſuch Engagements,</hi> have raiſed theſe doubts to the hopes of a new diſtraction.</p>
            <p>Beſides the Novity of a ſtrange and unheard of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement to be impoſed, other Diſcontents and heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burnings are cheriſhed, as in the Nobility to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truded from their Priviledges and Rights of ſitting in the Houſe of Parliament as Peers, to joyn with the Commons in the debate and handling the weighty affairs of the Common-wealth, as that thoſe Lords who have been active and aſſiſtant, both in their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates and Countenance, to promote the good of it during theſe Diſtractions, may think themſelves neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected and ill-rewarded to be now debarred from their Ancient and Native Liberty of Voting in the Houſe. The Reaſon of the Parliaments enjoyning of the Peoples ſubſcribing to this Engagement, reſts upon
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:116061:38"/>
the iſſue of theſe Queſtions. <hi>Whether there be a Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity or not of entring into ſuch League or Engagement: Whether the Conqueſt be fully made, or there need no En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement for compleating it? Whether the Kingdom of</hi> Ireland <hi>be reduced and brought into it's former relation and commerce with this of</hi> England, <hi>that there be no dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger or fears of breaking out again, when it ſhall be ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced? Whether through and by reaſon of the continuance of theſe Diſtractions, which the Parliament would put a period unto, were they not ſo much oppoſed and inveighed againſt, this of</hi> England <hi>be not in danger of looſing their ancient Rights and claims, their Freedom and Priviledges of Commerce and Traffique, which heretofore they have enjoyed?</hi> 
               <note n="a" place="margin">See this Queſtion in part cleared, <hi>pag.</hi> 40. in the Scots part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking with the King con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning one remarkable Article of the large Treaty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed upon, <hi>Auguſt</hi> 1641.</note> 
               <hi>Whether that of</hi> Scotland <hi>remain in the ſame condition of Amity and Brotherhood, as in their League and Covenant with</hi> England <hi>they at firſt united in? Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther whileſt that is in diſpute, we may reſt ſecure from an hoſtile Invaſion from them or Forreigners? Whether by theſe unneceſſary Diſputes and diſſentions here at home, the Common-wealth be not in danger to looſe that in the twink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of an eye, which hath coſt ſo much Treaſure, Induſtry and Blood (for the Powers</hi> that be, <hi>once ſhaken &amp; becoming weak, will ſoon fall)</hi> moſt men being apt to lay hold on the <note n="b" place="margin">
                  <hi>Noli in ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducum paric<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem inclinare,</hi> Lipſius Polit.</note> Polititian's advice <hi>[Not to lean on a weak and tot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering wall]</hi> The Judgment and knowledge of deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this, reſts in the Prudence and Experience of the State: who after a long time caſting and conſulting what was fitteſt to be done, what ſafeſt courſe to be taken for the ſtrengthning and ſupport of a firm and preſent Government, have Reſolved upon an Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall Engagement in ſuch manner and form as to their Wiſdoms ſeems moſt expedient, and They have ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly Declared and Ordained, that They know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:116061:38"/>
the juſtneſs of their Cauſe, ought in relation to the ſecurity and maintenance of their Power, to the Preſervation of a firme and laſting Peace, to uſe all expedient and lawfull means againſt the violent and reſtleſs Oppoſition of their Enemies; None ſo ſafe as by an Engagement and Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thereunto, Which if throughly weighed, croſſeth no former Vow or Oath either of Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Covenant, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>See the</hi> Oath of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance and Supremacie and why the taking it was enjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in this Treatiſe, <hi>pag.</hi> 51.</note> Oath of Allegiance or Supremacie, the Subſcriber <hi>only promiſing to be true and faithful to the Common-Wealth as it is now eſtabliſhed without King or Houſe of Lords.</hi> Not that the Nobility are thereby ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded for ever from their Priviledges, as to ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Parliaments, if theſe continued Diviſions beget not an univerſall ruin taking away the ſucceſſion of Parliaments to be hereafter had, nor from an Envy or Neglect had by the Houſe of Commons to take the Lords away, as hath been of late ſeditiouſly given out (for ſo the Gentry (of which the Parliament them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves conſiſt) being in the next Rank to the Nobili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, may fear their turn is next to be thrown from their ſtation alſo and all become Levelled) but that the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons and Eſtates of ſuch of the Lords as have aſſiſted the Court of Parliament in the time of their extremi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties may hence be preſerved from ruine, as of others alſo of the Nobility whom the Enemy reckons ſince their firſt engaging for the King, to be offenders now, for their late ſubmitting to their Compoſitions for Delinquency, for their complying with the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Votes; howbeit thereby they are free from mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation for the future, whileſt the Parliament main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and keep up their Power. Wherefore it is reſolved that an univerſal Engagement ſhall be had as a Bond
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:116061:39"/>
and League to bring all men into one and the ſame judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that from an <note n="a" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Lambard's</hi> Eirenarch. lib. 1. cap. 2. in in his Tract on K. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. His Writ direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the High Sheriff of <hi>Kent</hi> for the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>claiming a Peace, where he ſpeaks firſt of uniting mindes, then of reſtraining hands as a means to the Preſervation of the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Peace.</note> Unity of mindes, a Reſtraining of the hands may enſue, in order to the ſetling of a firm and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Peace. Admit that theſe Doubts were unqueſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable, theſe Dangers ſo removed and taken away, to our beſt advantage and ſecurity, that there needed no Engagement or League to bring all men into one and the ſelf ſame minde; yet the conſtant prejudice and ill-will which the Enemy hath to the Parliament and their Proceedings, cauſeth him, with many more of his kinde and ſpirit, to diſlike and refuſe the Engagement, becauſe the Parliament hath enjoyned it, and for no other cauſe, then to quarrel with and oppoſe their Authority.</p>
            <p>The other ſort of High Treaſon, wherewith the Parliament ſtands charged, is, <hi>The making a new</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">See the <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford</hi> Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, page 21.</note> 
               <hi>Great-Seal, counterfeiting the Kings:</hi> Obſerve Sir the juſtneſs of ſuch Charge. The Great-Seal an inſtrument of State, <hi>whereby Juſtice is derived and diſtributed to the People,</hi> as the divided Members at <hi>Oxford</hi> do confeſs, being ſurreptitiouſly and vafrouſly taken away from the Parliament, the Repreſentative Body of the People, contrary to the Truſt repoſed in the Keeper of the ſame, the making of a new one cannot be rightly judged Counterfeiting, within the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <note n="c" place="margin">25 <hi>Edw:</hi> 3.</note> Statute. Counterfeiting is a cloſe and covert act againſt the knowledge and privity of a Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perior and lawful Power, damnified by ſuch Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeiting; nor is every thing which is made to the mould by which 'tis made, a ſimply Counterfeiting:
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:116061:39"/>
The quality of the offence is diſcerned in the maner of the offending, and the making a Law commonly relates to ſome preterite crime or fraud: Now you will believe it is no where to be found upon Record, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to ground a Law, That a King and Parliament have at any time made uſe of any Great-Seal, to croſs or thwart each others Actings: Many other Accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations of this kinde are charged on them, <note n="*" place="margin">See the ſame Declaration, pag. 27.</note> as <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbers of the Peace, Authors and Fomentors of this,</hi> they call, <hi>Rebell on,</hi> and what elſe Malice and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge can invent divulge to render Them and their Actions infamous. But to return and ſhew the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aliſt his next hopes of prevailing, ſhadowed out even now. By attempting to bring in any Forreign Force, how wilde or barbarous ſoever they be, how hard to get them out again out of this plentiful and flouriſhing King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, yeelding them all proviſions, all Habiliments of War to ſtrengthen themſelves in This, as to provide for their next attempt elſwhere after they have deſtroyed and haraſſed This, not knowing how to diſtinguiſh be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Presbyterian, Independent</hi> and <hi>Royall</hi> Party, and this to be driven on by him (in an hazardous and uncertain way) out of revenge and thirſt to regain unto himſelf his power again, long ſince forfeited through his miſtaken Loyalty, certainly through his diſaffection to his Native Brethren of the ſame Kingdom; or without conſidering, which wiſe men ſhould, that a ſmall Forreign Force, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs aided by a diſcontented Faction here at home, will not do the work, a great one will deſtroy and overrun them alſo, which is eaſie and obvious to every vulgar ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to foreſee<hi>:</hi> for what Forreigner can be thought of to invade this Kingdom, whileſt the Natives thereof are
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:116061:40"/>
true unto &amp; at unity within themſelves? If it be objected, <hi>That the Subjects of This, taking up Arms to defend themſelves will prove a leading caſe to the People in other States and Kingdoms to do the like.</hi> Tis anſwered, The Government of This differs from all Forms of Government in other Nations, This being no abſolute but a limited and mixt Monarchy where the King is (as a great <note n="a" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bracton lib</hi> 4.</note> Lawyer takes his Dimenſion) <hi>Vniverſis minor, habet Superiores, Deum, Legem per quam factus eſt Rex, Curiam ſcilicet Comi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, Barones, &amp;c.</hi> The Laws Cuſtoms and Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of This are diſtinct and different from all other Nations in the Chriſtian world, others being Free-States ſimply and abſolutely Monarchies, or Powers inforcing and conforming all under them to ſlavery and vaſſaladge. So that if a Forreigner ſhall at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to invade This, it cannot be deemed he doth it from a ſenſe of a like ſuffering with the King or to aſiſt Him, rather to enrich himſelf, to prey upon the wealth and opulencie of a fruitful and flouriſhing Kingdom. Your laſt Objection, <hi>That the Army's moſt noted</hi> 
               <note n="b" place="margin">Mr. <hi>H. P.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Preacher is</hi> (as you have heard) <hi>a diſguiſed Jeſuite;</hi> Other the like Falſhoods put upon him, of late reported, which few men beſides the reporters do believe and ſcarſly they. If theſe Objections prove untrue or eaſily anſwered, the diſgrace will recoyle and injure them who lay them on. Sir if a man hath a minde to quarrel 'tis eaſie to finde a ſtaffe. Your Eminencie and Credit in your Country let in two Inconveniencies, A danger to be tempted by the oppoſite Party to comply and fall in with them, when mean and weak men are let alone, The other that it will fare with you in your Defection as ſpots and ſoiles in fine cloth; the finer the cloth the eaſilier the ſoiling is diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:116061:40"/>
in ordinary and courſe Cloths it is not ſo. No queſtion there are thoſe in ſeveral parts of our Neighbor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Counties who may inſtill into your Ears a likelyhood of the King's Party's prevailing, upon their prevailing the Dangers whereunto you and the reſt of His Enemies are ſubject, alſo the weakneſs, the often failings, the inique or unfit Proceedings of the Parliament, in prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for the preſent Perſons of a lower Degree then ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary to Places and Offices of Truſt; when as They were forced thereunto in that men of an higher rank <hi>diſcontented that their ſide cannot prevaile</hi> refuſe to bear ſuch Offices: In their Fining and Puniſhing the King's Party for De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquency, although not in ſo high and ſevere a way as the King's Party would have Puniſhed Them in caſe they had prevailed; In continuing Taxes and Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons upon their fellow Subjects for the maintenance of their Power and Army, Their Enemies not weighing the exigence and neceſſities which the Parliament is forced unto, but moved by their own prejudice and ſpleen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Proceedings of that Court, and reſolvedly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged for the King to make ſuch men as you to be of their Party, but that we know you can out-argue them, the ſtrength and quickneſs of their and their Party's argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments reſulting meerly from their pretence of Loyalty, or from that fierceneſs &amp; height of ſpirit occaſioned through the greatneſs of their Eſtates, therefore envying and are troubled to be over-born by men of lower fortunes. And this may give the hint of the vain ſurmiſe, <hi>That the Parliaments Deſign is to make the Eſtates of all men equall, to introduce a Levelling,</hi> when as men of great eſtates and ſpirits are armed with power to oppreſs and ſide with an Enemy againſt their meaner Brethren.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:116061:41"/>
Sir, If there be but a Defection in part, or abatement of conſtancy, which every occurrent of diſcontent height<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by your ſpirit, will or may ſoon turn into a totall De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in Perſons ſo eminent as you, in other Counties as in this, conſider what a Revolution of all things muſt then happen, how dangerous and fatall the effects will be, to render all men in all places engaged any way for the Parliament interpretably againſt the King, all Towns and Counties not conſonant to the King's will when this War began, to be anew queſtioned, all Places and Offices by Ye conferred, all Commiſſions and Grants by Ye made, all Conſtitutions by Ye, or under Your Authority eſtabliſhed, to be diſturbed (the Perſons accepting and inveſted in the ſame, expoſed to Reproach and Scorn) by a new moulding and alteration to be had upon a Re-Conquering, in caſe ſuch a chance ſhould befall this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and in mans apprehenſion cannot, unleſs your Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions ſhall let in ſuch Confuſion and Miſery, That thoſe who have been your Friends, ſhall upon Punctilioes &amp; pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Differences become your Enemies &amp; Accuſers, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards a prey themſelves to the firſt and common Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. Your active and conſtant Induſtry cannot degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate into a revolting now. This reciting your Actions here, will aſſoil you from the ſuſpition; and leave a deeper Impreſs of your meritings, then any outward commerce or compliance can raze out. You may for ought we know deal with as reſerved a ſubtilty to promote your firſt undertakings, as the Adverſe part think that you do to promote theirs. Laſtly, this you may ſee in the ſum of all, That if the prevailing Party in a Diviſion ſhall di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide according to their varying judgments, then ſubdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide, after ſubdivide again, there will be no end of ſuch
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:116061:41"/>
Dividings, untill the number of your whole Army be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced into few or none, and ſhattered in pieces, as your Enemies would have it, <hi>even as duſt before the winde.</hi> For inſtance ſake; The Kingdom did at firſt divide into a Party for the King, another for the Parliament, The Parliaments Party upon their Conqueſt did divide into <hi>Presbyterian, Independent;</hi> the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> if they ſhall prevail, may divide into a Scottiſh rigid <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> and an Engliſh <hi>Presbyterian</hi> of a milder teſt, and to be new moulded to the Conquerours faſhion: If the <hi>Independent</hi> ſhall prevail, they may rend into new <hi>Sects</hi> and <hi>Diviſions,</hi> and the prevailing party in ſuch Sects may divide again, ſo there wil be no end of Dividing till all be loſt and ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered. Neither is it your, or your oppoſite parties fault a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, but the fault of both to weaken and conſume Ye both. And what my fault is (the weakeſt of the Well-willers to your accord) I ſhall as willingly liſten and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit unto: I fear my plain dealing, which you'l ſay might have been ſpared, and my ſelfleſs blameable. No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your faithfull Friend to ſerve you. <hi>S. W.</hi>
               </signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>February</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
